好长的告示
How long De Gao Shi
欧洲
字幕制作 SlimChen
字幕翻译 SlimChen
- 这部电影在欧洲发行之前
- The poster that came out in Europe,
它的海报已张贴在英国乃至全欧的街头
at least in England,I believe, before the movie was released
in Europe said,
上面写道:一波横扫美国的惧浪
"The wave of terror that swept across America."
库布里克恰到好处的掌控了观众的心理
And Kubrick controlled the posters very carefully.
当你再观察一眼 便会觉得恍然大悟
Now,it made you do a double take.
我记得在欧洲看到这张海报时
I remember seeing it in Europe.
我还是美国广播新闻台驻罗马分社的社长
I was the Rome Bureau Chief at the time for ABC News.
我仍记得当时的情景
And I remember looking at it.
上面写着：一波横扫美国的惧浪
It said, The wave of terror that swept across America.
他在说什么？
What's he talking about?
接着你会意识到...
And you'd sort of think that he was talking about...
他说的是 小说《闪灵》所带来的冲击
the impact of the book The Shining.
也许是
Maybe.
而电影对社会的影响就像刚才说的那样吗？
The impact of the movie that had just opened over there?
也许是
Maybe.
但并不准确
It didn't quite fit.
那股席卷全美的恐怖之潮
The wave of terror that swept across America
从缅甸州的波特兰 刮到 俄勒冈州的波特兰*
from Portland, Maine,to Portland, Oregon,
*美国有两座名为 波特兰 的城市
它是由种族屠杀引起的 那是 白人高举斧头
was the genocidal armies and the white men with their ax
清除了一切 并引入了采掘工业以及其它的技术
clearing it all and bringing in extractive industries, among many other good things as well.
但那可是席卷全美的恐惧之潮
But that was the wave of terror that swept across America,
当然也吓坏了美国印第安人
terrifying, of course, the American Indians.
237号房间
《闪灵》九调查
采访
- 我在莱斯特广场影院看了这部电影
- I went in to see this movie in Leicester Square Movie Theater,
就在伦敦莱斯特广场旁边
right near Leicester Square in London.
对当时 我记忆犹新...
And I remember it quite clearly from...
我甚至记得当时的座位
I can even remember the seats we were sitting in.
现在要是能回到那个电影院 我可以指出来给你看
If I went back to that theater,I could point them to you,
是在后排靠左的位置
sort of near the back and over to the left.
电影开场时 直升机令人毛骨悚然的噪音就吓到我了
From the moment of the opening astonishing helicopter shot, I was terrified.
我不知道什么会到来
I had no idea what was coming.
我还记得 坐在椅子前端
I remember sort of sitting on the front edge
以防自己摔倒
of my theater seat there to keep from falling off.
我还用左手握住我的皮带扣
And I remember gripping my belt buckle with my left hand,
应该是...对 是我的左手 防止自己从椅子上吓摔倒
I think it was... yes, my left hand,sort of to keep from falling off
并控制住我看电影时的恐惧
the edge of the seat and to try to control my terror as I watched this movie.
我真的不知道会发生什么
I had no idea what was coming.
我还没读过原作
I hadn't read the book.
也没怎么看到过海报
I had barely seen any of the posters.
我记得电影放完后 我震惊了
And I remember that I was stunned when the movie was over.
我们离开电影院 到停车场 、开车回去
We left the theater, went in... down into our underground car park to get into the car to leave.
当我们开出地下车库时
And as we were driving up out of the car park,
我坐在左边的后座上
I was sitting in the back left seat.
我在回想 那是什么？到底是什么？
I was thinking, "What was that? What was that?
是什么东西？是鬼吗？是不是鬼？
"What was it? What was it? What was it?"
我记得当哈洛伦和丹尼交谈时
And I think my visual imagination
我的目光停留在那个卡路美特牌发酵粉罐子上
looked at that Calumet baking powder can,
哈洛伦脑袋右后方的那个
the one right behind Hallorann's head when he was talking to Danny.
我清楚"卡路美特"的含义
I knew what "calumet" meant.
*是北美印第安人用来表示和睦的烟斗
是 和睦烟斗*
It meant "peace pipe."
接着我想:和睦烟斗 印第安人
And I thought to myself, "peace pipe, Indians.
我的天哪
"Oh, my goodness,
他们在影片中随处可见
they're all over the place in that movie."
- 输的人要做家务
- The loser has to keep America clean.
- 我马上和朋友说:
- And I suddenly said to my friends：
"这个电影是关于印第安人种族屠杀的"
"That movie was about the genocide of the American Indians."
他们说:"你在说什么？"
And they said: "What are you talking about?"
接着我开始解释
And I started explaining it,
因为我注意到了那个卡路美特牌发酵粉罐子
because I'd noticed the Calumet baking soda can.
我们第一次见到这种罐子
In the first... the first time we seen one,
那是一个站立着的罐子
it's a single baking powder can straight on.
你能够清楚的看到整个词语 "卡路美特"
And you can see the whole word, "Calumet,"
所以这是毋庸置疑的
so there's no duplicity,
就像那对双胞胎女孩所代表的
like the little girls represent later.
这是个可靠的事实
This is an honest truth,
一个夹在他们之间的和睦烟斗
an honest peace pipe between them.
我们另一次看到发酵粉罐子
The other time we see the Calumet baking powder cans
《闪灵》男主角扮演者
是在杰克·尼克尔森*和格雷迪对话时
is when they're very carefully placed
它们在尼克尔森脑袋后面
behind Jack Nicholson's head when he's talking to Grady.
- 别戳我软肋了 格雷迪先生
- No need to rub it in,Mr. Grady.
我一出去就会解决那个问题
I'll deal with that situation as soon as I get out of here.
- 那里大概有六七个罐头叠在那儿
- There's about six or seven of them stacked up,
同时朝着不同的方向
and they're all turned different ways,
所以你不能只凭其中一个解读出来
and you can't read any one of them completely.
我一直将此理解为破碎和欺骗的和睦烟斗
It's... I've always interpreted those as being broken, dishonest peace pipe treaties.
格雷迪和杰克他们俩
They're not... these two guys,Grady and Jack,
他们对彼此并不真诚
are not being honest with each other.
格雷迪想借杰克之手杀了他全家
Grady is trying to get Jack to go kill his family
施行种族灭绝的犯罪
and commit genocide,
这部电影 从更广义的角度上来说
in the larger sense of the movie.
我是说 库布里克
You know, I mean, Kubrick often,
在他的很多作品中 常以谜题结局
in many of his movies, he will end them with a puzzle
因此当你走出影院 他总会让你说:
so that he forces you to go out of the theater saying,
"电影到底在说什么？"
"What was that about?"
同时 他还会在道具布景中
And he would put things in the scenes
使用一些证人道具
that he knows will be,among other things,
作为人们解读电影主题时的关键
like confirmers when people start to try to figure out what the movie is about.
我们知道 他很在意细节
And we know he took this kind of care.
有一本书里的照片
There's a photograph in one of the books
真实展现了库布里克
that actually shows Kubrick
对储藏室里货架的细致布局
carefully arranging objects on the shelves in that dry goods room.
后来 我苦思冥想
I thought afterwards,
"为什么我可以看到其他人看不到的东西？"
"How come I saw this and a lot of other people didn't?"
我意识到了
And I've thought about it.
原因是多方面的
It's a combination of factors.
首先 我在芝加哥长大
First, I grew up in Chicago and, therefore,
就在卡路美特海港北部
just north of the Calumet Harbor
因此在夏天 我能够在墨西哥湖边
and spent summers up in the sand dunes of Michigan,
和沙子一起愉快玩耍
around on the other side of Lake Michigan.
父亲会带着我和妹妹（姐姐）
My father took me and my sister out
收集印第安陶器碎片
to collect little bits of Indian pottery.
在1980年 黎巴嫩五年内战时期
I'd already...I'd already covered, at that point in 1980, five years of the Lebanese civil war.
我作为社长 采访了
I was, at that point, covering John Paul ll.
*罗马天主教第264任教宗
若望·保禄二世*
I was the Rome Bureau Chief.
我还记得他的讲话...
And listening to what he was saying about...
他亲身经历过大屠杀
because he had experienced the Holocaust at its epicenter
以及其他动乱
and also other horrors.
因此当我在看《闪灵》时
And so all of those factors
这些因素在我脑海中闪现出来
were very much alive in my mind when we went to see The Shining,
而我还以为 它不过是库大神制作的
which I just thought was going to be some kind of horror movie
一部简单的恐怖电影
by this great moviemaker.
而当这些因素蜂拥而至时
And all of those coming together along with the little key,
那个卡路美特罐子
the Calumet baking soda can,
就成了我们在回去的车内争论时
is why I just happened to tune to it as we were driving up out of that underground parking garage
解开这道谜题的钥匙
just off Leicester Square.
- 1980年 电影刚上映我就去看了
- I first saw the movie in 1980 when it first came out
应该是看了两次
and saw it probably two times.
我记得那张滑雪者的海报
I can say that I remembered the skier poster.
那个让我百思不得其解的东西
That is one thing that really stuck with me.
还有窗户
And the window.
那扇办公室里的窗户
The window in the office,
又一个让我极度抓狂的设定
that's another thing that really stuck with me.
我记得 报纸上写出 人们看过后
I remember, you know, in the newspapers afterwards,
对电影很失望
people being disappointed.
我还记得
And I remember people that I knew,
在和认识的人交谈后
yes, in dialogue afterwards,
他们很失望 觉得电影不够恐怖
being disappointed that it was not more a horror film.
但是 库导出品 必属精品
Well, no Kubrick film's really just a regular movie.
对于对句话的理解
I understood that from,
是我在十岁时 第一次看《2001：太空漫游》
well, when I was 10 years old and I first saw 2001.
我离场了
I walked away.
我心里想:
I thought, This is a film
这是一部会让我思考的电影
that's supposed to make me think.
- 我第一次感到虔诚
- I had my first religious experience
是在1968年看《2001：太空漫游》的时候
seeing the film 2001: A Space Odyssey in 1968.
我是个热爱艺术的小神童
I was a smart kid and liked art,
可我一点也不喜欢看电影
but I really did not like movies
觉得电影不是真正的艺术
and thought that they were really a substandard art.
你知道 那时的电影
And, you know, films like
都是《窈窕淑女》《怪医杜立德》之类的烂片
My Fair Lady and Doctor Dolittle were out.
60年代是电影艺术的惨淡期
And it was a rather pathetic time in the '60s for films.
我的女朋友先提到了这部影片
And my girlfriend, she pulled up
她跟我说 昨晚她看了部电影
and told me that she'd seen a movie the night before
想再看一遍
and she wanted to see it again.
然后她带着我去电影院去看了
So she took me to the theater,the Cinerama Dome,and I watched it.
我这辈子都没想到过
And I had never in my life envisioned that a movie
一部电影可以做成这样
could do what this movie was doing.
效果上 它让我大开眼界
And it was showing me things that I had never seen,
内容上 也很考验观众的思维能力
and it was intellectually challenging.
从各个方面来看 这都是一部艺术巨作
And it was an artistic masterpiece in every way,
从声效 到视觉 到情节
from the soundtrack to the visuals to the story line.
当影片结束时 我甚至不能站起来
And when the movie ended,I couldn't get out of my seat.
我震惊了
I was frozen in the seat,
完全被自己看到的东西麻痹了
completely paralyzed by what I'd just witnessed.
最后是引座员把我带了出去
And the usher actually had to come and get me out.
厅内只有我和女友两个人
And I was the last person,me and her.
我百感交集的走出了电影院
And I staggered out of the theater
成了一个更完整的人类
completely changed as a human being
在那时 我决定
and decided at that moment
我余生最想做的事
that the only thing that I wanted to do for the rest of my life
就是去拍出类似这样的电影
was to make films in one fashion or another.
而我已经做到了
And so I have done that.
因此我要感谢库布里克和他的《2001：太空漫游》
So I owe Stanley Kubrick and his film 2001: A Space Odyssey
感谢他让这一切成为我的生活
everything for everything that I have become in my life, so...
- 在研究库布里克的电影之前
- I saw a number of Kubrick films
我就看了他的许多作品
before I had an academic interest in him.
1980年 我去看了《闪灵》
And then I went to see The Shining in 1980.
坦白的说 我当时觉得它不怎么样
And frankly,I didn't think that much of it.
我看过他的其它作品
I thought the other Kubrick films that I'd seen
都比这部优秀很多
were far superior.
后来 我回想 这部电影...
But as I thought about the film afterwards...
就算我没有刻意的去想它...
and even when I wasn't thinking about it...
仍有一些东西在扰乱我的思路
there were things that bothered me about it.
好像我忽略了什么
It seemed as if I had missed something.
所以我又回影院二刷
And so I went back to see it again.
我开始注意到一些之前忽略了的细节
And I began to see atterns and details that I hadn't noticed before
于是我一遍又一遍的看
And so I kept watching the film again and again and again.
我是一名历史学家
And since I'm trained as an historian
我主要研究
and my special expertise
德国与纳粹德国的的历史
is in the history of Germany and Nazi Germany in particular,
因此我越来越相信
I became more and more convinced
在这部电影中
that there is,in this film,
对纳粹大屠杀 有着隐蔽的暗示
a deeply laid subtext that takes on The Holocaust.
我觉得那台打字机
I think it probably was the typewriter,
那台德国牌的打字机 看上去也许是随便找来的
which was a German brand,which might seem arbitrary,
但在那时 我已经很了解库布里克
but by that time,I knew enough about Kubrick
我知道他的影片中 几乎没有什么是随便的
that most anything in his films can't be regarded as arbitrary,
尤其是道具和颜色的使用
that anything...especially objects and colors
以及音乐和其他方面 或多或少都是故意的
and music and anything else,probably have some intentional as well as unintentional meaning to them.
这让我很费解
And so that struck me.
为什么是一台德国牌打字机？
Why a German typewriter?
由此
And in connection with that,
我在电影中发现了数字 42
I began to see the number 42 appear in the film.
而在德国历史中 你将数字 42
And for a German historian,if you put the number 42
和一台德国打字机放在一起
and a German typewriter together,
你得到的是纳粹大屠杀
you get the Holocaust,
因为德国在1942年
because it was in 1942 that the Nazis made the decision
通过了消灭犹太人的决议
to go ahead and exterminate all the Jews they could.
独裁的他们就像杀人机器一样进行屠杀
And they did so in a highly mechanical, industrial, and bureaucratic way.
所以我深深地意识到
And so the juxtaposition of the number 42
数字42和打字机的并列使用
and the typewriter was really where it started for me
是为了在电影中表达历史事实
in terms of the historical content of the film.
当然 "阿德勒"在德文中的意思是"鹰"的意思
Of course "adler"in German means "eagle."
而老鹰是纳粹德国的象征
And eagle, of course,is a symbol of Nazi Germany.
也是美国的象征
It's also a symbol of the United States.
库布里克通常会用老鹰
And Kubrick generally has recourse to eagles
来象征国权
to symbolize state power.
*澳裔政治学家 历史学家
库布里克读过劳尔·希尔伯格*的论作
Kubrick read Raul Hilberg's
《欧洲犹太人的灭绝》
The Destruction of the European Jews.
而希尔伯格书中的主题
And Hilberg's major theme in there
就是关于杀人武器的
is that he focuses on the apparatus of killing.
他还特别强调纳粹的独裁性
And he emphasizes how bureaucratic it was
并解释了名单和打字机的的含义
and how it was a matter of lists and typewriters.
斯皮尔伯格在《辛德勒的名单》中采用了这一指代
Spielberg picked that up in Schindler's List, of course.
我是说 电影开场就出现了打字机和名单
I mean, the film begins with typewriters and lists
并以名单结束
and ends with a list,of course.
电影就是这样传达它的主题的
And so that informs.
我曾在劳尔·希尔伯格访问阿尔比恩学院时
and I had a chance to talk to Raul Hilberg.
和他交谈过
He visited Albion College.
他说自己和库布里克在这一点上有着共识
And he said that he and Kubrick corresponded about this.
他之后知道了另一个事实
And the fact that he read it then, in the 1970s,
十九世纪七十年代 掀起了一阵
when there was a big wave of interest in Hitler
研究希特勒 大屠杀以及纳粹的浪潮
and the Holocaust and the Nazis,I think...
我觉得这说明 那台打字机
I think just tells us that that typewriter,
那台德国牌打字机
that German typewriter...
在指出一个异常重要的历史事件的同时
which by the way, changes color in the course of the film,
也改变了这部电影的基调
which typewriters don't generally do...
这发挥出了
is terribly,terribly important
打字机不一般的作用
as a referent to that particular historical event.
- 我曾在电影资料馆工作了十年
- I worked in a film archive for a decade,
那感觉就像 以快进的速度
kind of like fast-forwarding
一天浏览十次二战
through World War II ten times a day.
但是 你知道 当你一遍又一遍的
But, you know, like,when you see things
看东西时
over and over and again,
它们的含义也在改变
their meanings change for you.
比如说 当你看到这些二战的新闻影像资料时
Like, when you see these... see,like, World War ll newsreels,
看了一段时间过后 你会觉得
like, after a while,you come to realize
这些影像都是假的
that it's all faked on film.
你看到的不是诺曼底登录
You are not seeing troops storming Normandy.
你看到的是军队登录好莱坞的一个沙滩
You're seeing troops storming a beach in Hollywood.
再比如 你看到的不是一架飞往日本的战机
You know, like, you're not seeing a plane flying to Japan.
而是飞往新墨西哥州
You're seeing a plane flying over, you know, New Mexico.
你所看到的都是舞台上的英雄主义
What you're really being shown is, like, staged heroism.
你可以看到士兵们在车上
You know, like, you're seeing men moving with machines,
但是你却看不到他们交谈
but you're not seeing what they're talking about.
我认为这正是库布里克的表现方式
And I think that that's something that Kubrick plays on.
他既利用你所看到的画面
Like, he plays on your acceptance of visual infor...
也利用着你忽略的画面
and also your ignorance of visual information.
比如 他经常使用一些你在角落中才能看到的
Like he'll often, like,put little special clues
细微线索
that you see,like, in the corner.
每一个场景都有着匪夷所思的设定
Every scene,there's an impossibility,
比如这台没有电线的电视
like the TV doesn't have a cord
或者更简单直白一些的 比如
or even something as simple as,like, them...
他们入住酒店的时候带了很多行李
they, like...they bring too much luggage up.
在电影中 杰克瞥了一眼
They, like... Jack, you know,glances over at a pile
他们带来的那一堆行李
of their luggage that they brought,
大概有一辆轿车那么大
and ifs about the size of a car.
此外 影片中还有很多笑点
You know, a lot of it is jokes.
比如 在游览时
Like, they're taking the tour.
他们穿过迷宫前的那条路
They're crossing the street from the maze
去参观车库
to go check out the garage.
有一辆车眼看着就要撞上他们
Like, a car is just about to hit them.
但在发生之前却剪掉了
And then it cuts right before.
浓缩
- 我在上映之前就看过这部电影
- I had anticipated the film
*《闪灵》作者
同时也阅读了史蒂芬金*的小说
and had read the Stephen King novel
我发现这是一个非常吸引人的故事
before the film came out and found it a very appealing story.
我花了很多时间
And I had spent a lot of time
去研究了科罗拉多州 埃斯蒂斯公园的斯坦利酒店
at the Stanley Hotel in Estes Park, Colorado,
这里是史蒂芬金写《闪灵》的灵感来源
which is where he was inspired to write the book The Shining.
因此 我对小说的创作背景比较了解
And so I, you know... I knew a little bit of the background.
而当电影上映时
And when Kubrick's film came out,
我是第一批看过的人
I was first in line to see it,of course.
但我很失望
And I was just really disappointed
我中途离场了
and walked out of the theater
想着我刚才看的是什么鬼东西
wondering what the hell I had just witnessed.
自那之后 我对史丹利·库布里克的崇拜
And, I... actually,my reverence for Stanley Kubrick
一落千丈
diminished after that.
尽管如此 我还是每隔几年就再看一遍
I was disappointed, but I still watched it every few years.
我不知道为什么会被
I couldn't understand why I was so attracted to watching a film
一部不喜欢的电影吸引着
that I actually didn't like.
而在看了这么多遍之后
And now in all these years later,
我知道它为什么是一部伟大电影了
I know why it is a great film.
是一部杰作
It is a masterpiece,
但不是绝大多数人所说的原因
but not for the reasons that most people think.
我们在和一个智商200的人打交道
We are dealing with a guy who has a 200 IQ.
我相信在斯坦利·库布里克
believe that when Stanley Kubrick
在完成《巴里·林登》之后 百无聊赖
finished with Barry Lyndon,he was bored.
他已经征服了电影场景的设计
He had conquered the filmmaking landscape.
他也做到了拍出一部又一部的伟大的作品
He had succeeded in making masterpiece after masterpiece,
他寂寞了
and he was bored.
《巴里·林登》也是一部无聊的电影
Barry Lyndon is a boring movie.
它拍摄完美
It is wonderfully shot.
服装精致
It is beautifully costumed.
但这是由一个寂寞的人拍出来的
But it is a film made by a guy who is bored.
我看的出来
And I could see that.
所以我觉得库布里克在《巴里·林登》之后就转型了
And so I think Stanley retreated after Barry Lyndon.
他开始研究一种新的类型
And he began working on a new kind of film,
一种他从未尝试过的类型
a film that had never been made before,
一部由一个寂寞的天才
a film that was made by a bored genius
在抛弃一切丰功伟绩之后
who had thoroughly emptied the jug of everything
所拍出的电影
that could be done in filmmaking.
他开始寻觅
And he was looking for the next thing.
*美国作家
他读了威尔逊·布赖恩·基*的《潜意识的诱惑》
And what he did was he began reading Subliminal Seduction
还有一些关于广告商是如何
and a number of other books which were about how advertisers
如何将 潜意识图片
were injecting...injecting images,subliminal images,
注入广告 来提高销量的书籍
into advertising to sell products more.
- "头屑去无踪,秀发更出众"
- "Suggestible trends".
- 比如在钻石金酒的广告中
- You know, there'll be an ad for Gilbey's Gin,
冰块内部是各种生殖器的形状和
and inside, the ice cubes will be various sex organs
一些其他的性暗示
and things to add a subliminal appeal to the ad.
库布里克去了这些广告公司
Kubrick went to these advertisers,
询问了这类广告的研究方法
and he asked them what their methods were.
并将这一方法
And then he took those methods
使用在《闪灵》中
and he applied them to The Shining.
《闪灵》里有许多潜意识画面
Inside The Shining are hundreds of subliminal images and shot line-ups.
这些画面
And what these images are telling
是非常恐怖和有着强烈性暗示意味的
is an extremely disturbing story about sexuality.
这一情节的潜台词
And the subtext of the story,
与其他情节不同
besides the other subtexts of the story,
它所说的是幽灵 魔鬼
is a story of haunted phantoms and demons
在两性方面 勾引着人类
who are sexually attracted to humans
并以人类为食
and are feeding off of them.
你不一定非得像我这样狂热的去发现这些
You'd have to be able to be a complete fanatic like I am in order to find all this,
我会告诉你我最钟意的发现
but, you know,I'll give you my favorite.
我最最钟意的那一个
I'm only gonna give you one,but I'll give you my favorite.
在电影一开头
When Jack meets Stewart Ullman in the office
当杰克与斯图尔特·厄尔曼在办公室会见时
at the very beginning of the movie
厄尔曼起身与杰克握手
and he reaches over to shake Jack Nicholson's hand...
让我们慢速播放这个场景
and so step through that scene frame by frame.
逐秒逐帧的看
And the minute,the moment,
当厄尔曼的手碰到杰克时
the frame that he and Jack Nicholson touch hands
*斯图尔特·厄尔曼扮演者
在巴里·尼尔森*
and right after the line that Barry Nelson says,
说了"很高兴见到你"之后
which is, "Nice to see you,"
你可以看到一个...
you can see that there's a paper...
一个放在桌上的文件盒
a paper tray on the desk.
当他们刚接触到彼此的手
And as soon as they touch hands,the paper tray
那个文件盒就变成了
turns into a very large straight-on hard-on
巴黎·尼尔森勃起的象征
coming out of Barry Nelson.
↑
呵呵呵呵呵呵
Yeah, it's hilarious.
这是个笑话 一个由库布里克构思的严肃笑话
It's a joke... a very serious joke... but a joke by Stanley.
诸如此类的电影中还有很多
And there's many of these in the film.
其中也有一些让人感到困扰
And very disturbing,some of them.
我的电影《魔术师库布里克》会告诉大家全部的细节
And this will all be in my film,Kubrick the Magician.
我再说一个
I'll give you one more.
一个更难发现的细节
This one's harder to find, okay?
首先你得知道 库布里克
And you have to know what Stanley Kubrick looked like
在拍《闪灵》时 长什么样
during the making of The Shining to know this one.
在影片的开场
But if you go to the opening credits
你逐帧的播放
and you pan the frame...
一帧一帧的看
you... you go through the frames,
在字幕"导演 斯坦利·库布里克"
right after it says "Directed by Stanley Kubrick,"
就要滚出屏幕时
as soon as his name passes off the frame,
暂停 你会发现 库布里克的面容
stop and you will see that the clouds have Stanley Kubrick
隐藏在了云层之中
airbrushed into them,his face...
包括他的胡子 头发 整个面庞
with the beard and the wild hair and the whole thing.
我知道这发现这个有点困难（看出来的请豆油我）
I know this one's a little harder to find.
我甚至...
And I will have to...
甚至需要把它PS出来 别人才能发现
I will have to Photoshop this one to show people it,
但这里绝对是把一张库布里克的照片
but there is definitely the photograph of Stanley Kubrick
在一帧里将其与云层叠画
in one frame airbrushed into the clouds.
- 在大多数电影中 叠化转场
- In most films,a dissolve is used
常被用在象征两个时间跨度较长的场景
to indicate a long passage of time between two scenes.
但在《闪灵》中 叠化转场的持续时间非常久
But in The Shining,the dissolves go on for so long
以至于它们能够创造出
that they create a superimposition,
由两个场景相互叠加作用出的新场景
where different scenes seem to be interacting with each other.
比如说 这里你有一个外景
For example,you have the exterior image
接着是一个酒店大堂的轨道平移拍摄
a tracking shot of the lobby
摄影机沿着西边的墙运动
of the camera moving along the western wall
酒店入口面朝南边
south towards the entrance.
你可以看到一个清洁员在拖地
And you see a janitor mopping the floor,
但叠化使这个画面看上去
but it looks like he's...
看上去像 他拿着一个巨大的拖把
it looks like a he's a giant, mopping,
在打扫森林
like, clearing the forest
因为那儿正好是森林里的一块空地
because he's mopping, like,a vacant area in the forest.
还有那个
And then the...
那个立着的梯子
then the ladder lines up...
和金字塔形的酒店外观同时出现
lines up with the pyramid form of the exterior of the hotel,
而在酒店外的场景中 金字塔三角形消失了
which, in the exterior set,disappears.
胡德堡   俄勒冈州
林线旅馆
远望酒店外景
埃尔斯特里制片厂   英格兰
就像不存在一样
Like, we don't see...
我们只在林线旅馆看到了金字塔形的屋顶
we only see that in the Timberline exteriors.
但在英格兰的拍摄场景中
But the England movie set exteriors of the hotel,
金字塔外形不见了
like, the pyramid is missing,
看起来 远望酒店
and it seems as if the hotel
只模仿建造了林线酒店的两侧
then takes both sides of the Timberline Hotel
这就像合二为一的手法
and then kind of, like,makes a composite of it.
因此 这种转换
So it's... you know,it's a perceptual shift
让角色看起来像是巨人
of making people look like giants,
也让酒店看起来或大或小
also making the hotel look larger or smaller than it is.
我认为这些东西让电影更丰满
I mean, these things kind of litter the movie.
但随着机位的移动
But then the shot goes on.
我们看到...
We see a...
看到一个门卫推着一台装有折叠床的货车
we see a janitor pushing a folded-up bed on wheels.
他后面跟着...
And then he's followed by another...
另一个人 抬着一个...
he's followed by another guy,who's carrying, like, one...
像是咖啡桌
like, one coffee table?
接着还有一个人抬着一张椅子
And then another... like, another guy is carrying one chair.
他们抬着这些轻货物是去哪儿呢?
Like, where are these guys going with, like, these light loads, you know?
然后我们看到杰克坐在沙发上 吃午饭
Then we see Jack sitting on a chair, eating lunch.
接着酒店管理员和他的助手
And the manager and his assistant crosses paths
穿过两个女人走的那条路上
with two women who...
正当管理员走到屏幕角落的时候
and just as he's in the corner of the screen...
你可以看到
you just see it for a second.
其中一个女人身上穿着写有 13 的衣服
You see one of the women is wearing, like, a 13,
写着13的运动衫
a number 13 jersey?
你听到了吗
Can you hear that?
我儿子在叫（这熊孩子）
My boy, yelling?
等我一下
Hold on one second.
我去看看（能不能打死他）...
I'm gonna see if I can...
我去让他老实点儿
I can see if I can calm him down.
杰克靠在沙发上
You know,so, like, he's like,
吃着三明治
leaning back and eating a sandwich.
他双腿之间夹着一本杂志
And he's got, you know,a magazine in his lap.
而在他起身向管理员打招呼时
And as he stands up to greet them,
他把杂志扔在了沙发上
he, like, throws it down.
如果你仔细观察...
And if you look at"look at...
看杂志的封面
look at it, you know,close up,
你会发现它是一本《花花女郎》
it's an actual Playgirl magazine.
在酒店的大堂里看《花花女郎》杂志
Yeah, a Playgirl magazine in the lobby of a hotel
而且就在上班的第一天 在他的老板面前
right in front of his boss,like on his first day at work.
没错
Yeah.
那一期的封面是 人们筹备新年
Like, the cover is like, people getting ready for New Year's.
书内有一篇关于乱伦的文章
There's an article about incest.
乱伦：为什么父母要带小孩睡觉←
*删减版无此情节
在电影的开头 丹尼受到了身体上的虐待*
At the beginning of the film,Danny's been physically abused.
但有一个关于
But there's a suggestion
他也被性侵的暗示
that he's been sexually abused as well.
有一个镜头
You know, so like,just in that one...
有一个镜头是各种复杂的事物
one shot, there's all these,like, you know, complex things
在画面背景中 碰到了一块儿
going on in the background,
就像是被设计
like things that are choreographed
让它们刚好联系起来
to match up exactly.
比如 我们看到一个人...
Like, we see a guy...
一个人背着...
we see a guy, carrying a...
背着一条地毯 进入楼上的房间
entering the room,carrying a rug.
而这个场景就要结束时
And by the time the scene is just ending,
我们看到他上楼了
we see him walking up the stairs.
就像他穿过了整个大堂
Like, he's crossed the entire place,
分秒不差
you know, timed exactly.
实在是...
I don't even...
好厉害
Yeah.
- 当厄尔曼带着托伦斯一家
- When Ullman is leading the Torrances
走出电梯 进入科罗拉多休息室时
out of the elevator and into the Colorado Lounge
在上一个场景中 大厅里有一堆行李箱
for the first time,there's a pile of suitcases.
而在叠化至这一场景时
And in the dissolve into that scene,
变成了一群游客
the scene before,a group of tourists
站在那儿
are standing in the lobby.
形成了行李箱和游客之间的叠化
And those tourists dissolve into the suitcases.
作为大屠杀历史的研究者
Now, as an historian of the Holocaust,
当时我就震惊了
I find that very, very striking
而这绝不是巧合
and certainly not accidental
因为叠化转场是一种画面上的结合
'cause he's using those sort of cross-dissolves.
这和那个梯子一样
Now, that could be,along with the ladder,
库布里克想要制造出实质的
where he's trying to make substantive connections
有迹可循的关联
as well as formal ones.
- 哦~厄尔曼办公室的窗户
- Oh, the window in Ullman's office,
美艳至极
it is absolutely beautiful.
一般的观众
The casual viewer isn't going to see
在库布里克的电影中是看不到如此多的细节的
so many things in Kubrick's films,
他们也许会感觉画面不舒服
although I think they may register unconsciously.
但是他们不能
You know, but they're not going to, you know,
不能道出个所以然
perceive perhaps these things
因为就像我说的
because as I've said,
库布里克让假的东西看起来真实
he presents them as being real.
《闪灵》是现实主义
You know, it's realism.
它并不是一部典型的恐怖片...
And it's not your typical horror...
只有在影片最后
you don't have a horror film
温蒂跑入冷色调的大厅里
except for this one section at the end,
到处都是蜘蛛网
right where Wendy walks in and the lobby is blue
你才觉得这是一部恐怖片
and you've got the cobwebs all around.
这就像
And it's almost like
在周末 看着正能量晨间剧时
a Saturday morning kind of horror film
突然出现了好几只贞子
suddenly there for a second.
你的反应会是
And you kind of go
"天哪 这些乱入的骷髅和蜘蛛网是个啥？"
Ooh, what is this with the skeletons and the cobwebs?"
有点儿庸俗
And it's kind of cheesy.
在那个场景之后
But then, after that,following that,
温迪跑在红色的走廊里
you've got her going down the red hallway,
在大屏幕上看 让人石化
which...on the big screen, that's petrifying.
所以我认为 之前的那种庸俗
So I think the kind of cheesiness before it
推动了红色走廊场景的建立
helps set up that red hallway.
哎我刚才说哪儿了？
So anyway, what was I saying?
噢对窗户
Right, the windows.
当杰克进入大厅
So you got... Jack has entered.
你可以看到
And you can see...you are...
库布里克向你展现
Kubrick shows you.
向你展现了这个大堂 你可以看到...
But he shows you this lobby,and you get to see...
随着杰克穿过大堂 你可以看到前方的电梯
as Jack moves across the lobby,you see the elevator beyond.
还有一条通道
And you see beyond that,a hallway.
你不知道它后面有多长
You don't see yet how far back it goes, you know,
对于后面那条路 你有印象
the other things back there,but you have an impression
这个地方是面朝酒店中间的
that this place is towards the middle of the hotel.
你只是印象中觉得
You just have that impression that it's towards
它面朝酒店中间
the middle of the hotel.
你跟着杰克从大厅进入总经理的办公室
And you go from the lobby into the general manager's office
接着是厄尔曼的办公室 窗户在那里
and then into Ullman's office, and there's this window.
一扇强有力的窗户
And the window's a powerful window.
我是说 阳关穿过玻璃 折射出耀眼的光芒
I mean, the light coming through there is glaring.
窗户就像一个角色
It's like a character in itself.
它像一个主宰者
It takes over.
你可以看到 一些杂乱弯曲 不吉利的树
And you've got these tendril-y,sinister kind of trees
种在窗户外面
that are outside the window.
你可以感觉到
And you've got...
光束抓住了一切
it's just such a forceful presence,
彰显着强大的存在感
this light that comes over everything.
但是你感到
And, you know...
这里有些不对劲
And there's something wrong with it.
肯定有不合常理的地方
There's something wrong with it,
我认为这显现出了一个错误
and I think it registers as something wrong.
这是一扇不存在的窗户
This is an impossible window.
它不存在
It's not... it is impossible.
它是实际上的不存在
It is physically impossible.
它不应该在那
It cannot be there.
它不可能出现
It should not be there.
酒店里没有地方设立这个窗户
There's no place in the hotel for this window to exist.
只有在...
It's only toward...
在影片的最后
finally,towards the end of the film,
你会意识到在厄尔曼的办公室后面
that you have the realization that there are several hallways
有好几条走廊
in succession behind the office.
当温迪走下楼
You see it when Wendy,
看到迪克·哈洛伦
when she's later down there and she sees Dick Hallorann's body
死去的尸体时
after he's been killed.
你知道她是在...在办公室后面的过道上
You have her behind... in that hallway behind the office.
我该怎么跟你描述酒店的平面图呢？
So really, now, what can I tell you about the maps?
不行 我得画个图
No, I did not sit down with graph paper.
我不按比例 画个草图
I did not even begin to attempt to do them to scale.
让我想一下
Let me see.
我不知道从哪个房间开始
I can't say which room I started off with.
我忘了
I don't remember.
我打算从...
I just went through and decided I was going to do...
我尽量说的详细一些...
try to do as much as I could,feeling that...
我认为 我可以划分出
I felt, eventually,that there were places
两个女孩被杀死的房间
that I could plot out, such as where the girls were killed.
我不是很确认
I was not absolutely sure at that point,
那个房间是不是
when I started out doing the maps,
我画地图的起始点
where the girls were killed.
（这段她说的乱and我翻的也乱...）
应该是在后面
But I felt that it was somewhere back around
他们居住的区域
the area where they lived.
房间号是...
Suite number, what?
他们住3号房
They lived at suite number 3.
- 当杰克坐在那儿打字时
- When Jack is sitting,typing at his typewriter,
温迪走出来 在他工作时
and Wendy comes in and interrupts him
打扰到了他
while he's working...
而在杰克的一个画面中...
and in one shot of Jack...
- 你今天写了很多吗？
- You get a lot written today?
- 坐在打字机前的那个镜头里
- Sitting at the typewriter,a one shot,
在他的后面
you look back behind him.
你可以很清楚的看到
And of course,you can see very clearly
因为库布里克是景深大师
'cause Kubrick was the master of depth of field.
他让一切处于焦距范围内 所以他能够让你
He kept everything in focus so he would have lots of space
注意到他故意设置的细节
in which to puts things that he wanted you to notice.
在这个镜头中 杰克坐在打字机前
And in the first shot,behind Jack sitting at his typewriter,
在他身后 大约10或12或者15英尺的墙边
back against a wall, behind him probably 10 or 12 or 15 feet
有一张椅子
is a chair.
接着是一个温迪说话的镜头
And then there's a switch to a one-shot of Wendy saying something.
- 嘿 天气预报说今晚下雪
- Hey, the weather forecast said it's gonna snow tonight.
- 接着镜头回到杰克身上
- And then the camera switches back to Jack,
他身后的椅子不见了
and the chair is gone.
- 下雪我有什么办法？
- What do you want me to do about it?
- 我和学生们总是乐此不疲
- And my students and I always have fun with that,
"是不是穿帮了？"
saying,"Well, continuity error?"
也许是
Could be.
也许刻意使然
Or it's not,and the answer, if it's not...
如果是穿帮
or if it was originally
那么库布里克发现了它 并决定保留
and then Kubrick saw it and decided to keep it,
这种山寨恐怖片的行为
is that he's parodying horror films
是在提醒观众 这不是一部简单的恐怖片
in order to remind you that this isn't just a horror film.
而在电影中 还有一幕 我认为
And there's another one in The Shining that's, I think,
更不容易被发现
less well-noticed.
我觉得这一点更真实可靠
And I think it's even more clearly substantive.
当丹尼第一次看到电梯血涌时
When Danny has his first vision of the elevator gushing blood
摄影机在向他移动
and the camera is tracking toward him,
穿过他卧室的门
past the open door of his bedroom
朝着走廊和浴室前移
and toward the hall and the bathroom,
接着横穿过道 到了浴室门口
the open bathroom door across the hall...
你可以看的出 他卧室门上
and his bedroom door, as you would expect a kid's door,
贴着很多动漫人物
has lots of cartoon characters on it
最明显的那一个贴纸
And, the one who is most apparent,
在门的右侧边缘
because it's right at the edge of the door
它是你可以看到的最完整的一个
and it's the largest one that you can see
也是在摄影机运动时 你能看到的最后一个人物贴纸
and it's the last one you can see as the camera moves past it,
它是七个小矮人中的一个
is one of the Seven Dwarves.
它叫迷糊鬼
And it happens to be Dopey,okay?
后来 在丹尼昏过去之后（删减版无此情节）
Subsequently,after Danny has passed out,
当温迪和儿科医生
Wendy and the pediatrician leave Danny's room.
离开丹尼的房间时
And as they do, they,of course, go out his door.
你又可以看到那扇门
And you again see the door,
贴着卡通人物的开着的门
the open door with all the cartoon characters on it,
迷糊鬼不在那儿了
and Dopey isn't there.
又是穿帮吗？
Now, again continuity error?
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
我觉得库布里克是在说
I think what Kubrick is saying is that before,
丹尼对世界有了更多的了解
Danny had no idea about the world, and now he knows.
他不再是一个迷糊鬼了
He is no longer a dope about things.
他被启发过了
He has been enlightened.
你说了算 劳埃德
- - Anything you say, Lloyd.
你说了算
Anything you say.
- 接着发生了意外
- The the advocaat is spilled.
荷兰产蛋酒洒了出来
There's the accident.
库布里克像是设计了
Kubrick is setting it up
一个圆 让人物绕着它走位
as where they come around in a circle,
我觉得摄影机就是这样运动的
'cause I feel like that's what the camera does.
我感觉摄影机在带着我们绕圈
I feel like the camera brings us around in a circle
带着我们回到原点
so that we're coming back.
洗手间似乎是在金色大厅上面
The bathroom seems to be overlaying the Gold Room and...
在洗手间 处理那个意外时
so that the advocaat situation
他们站立的地点大概和
in the bathroom is occurring about
在金色大厅发生的地点一致
in the same area that it did in the Gold Room.
- 他们使用摄影机
- They use the camera
在观众脑海里创造出一个看似合理的建筑
to create an emotional architecture in your mind
但同时 又证明你错了
but at the same time,showing you that it's false.
整个场景的可塑性如此之高
The set is complete...so completely plastic
以至于各种矛盾都堆积在你的潜意识中
that its contradictions pile up in your subconscious.
走出C3                                              进入C4
哈洛伦向...
Hallorann is showing...
向温迪展示了后面的情节中
showing Wendy, you know,the place where she will,
她会困住杰克的地方
you know, basically,entrap Jack...
无论是生理
entrap him both physically,
还是心理上 对杰克都是最后一击
but also, like, that will be the last straw for him,
这也是对酒店的最后一击
last straw for the management of the hotel.
在储藏室中 杰克决定
It's in the store room that he finally is like,
开始还击
"Okay.Now I'm gonna do it."
而那扇门的开启
And, you know,the opening of that door
是影片中唯一不可思议的
is the famous, like,only thing that's supernatural
无法解释的超自然情节
happens in the movie that can't be explained any other way.
是的
Yeah.
除了另一种说法
But except that it can be explained another way,
那就是 丹尼把他放了出来
in that Danny lets him out.
而我的确认为
I do have this idea that Danny
丹尼是自发的杀了他的父亲
is a lot more consciously murdering his father
而不是情节使然
than the narrative lets on.
我也说不清 很诡异
I don't know.It's weird.
比如 当温迪和杰克在休息室对峙时
Like, you notice how, like,Wendy's walking backwards
你有没有注意到 她是如何后退的
when she's having that confrontation with Jack in the lounge, you know.
她像是被什么往后拉
And she's being drawn up to the hexagonal hallway room.
而丹尼也是在那儿闪灵的
And you see Danny shining at the beginning of that.
他在屋子里
He's in his room,and there's, like,
眼睛里像有火焰闪烁
lights flickering in his eyes.
就像丹尼...
Like, is Danny drawing...you know,
在拉他的母亲后退 以使她能够
drawing his mother up the stairs so that she can, you know,
在高处击中杰克 像是一个诡异的金字塔
sacrifice Jack on top of that,you know, weird pyramid?
- 我曾经在丹佛做报道
- When I had a chance...when I was doing a story
我们去了埃斯蒂斯公园
out in Denver,we went up to Estes Park.
那是在旅游淡季
It was in the off-season.
在史丹利酒店 我请求和经理见一面
Went into the Stanley Hotel,and I asked to see the manager.
于是他们和他一起吃了中饭
And he came out, and we were just having lunch with him.
我问他：“可以采访你吗？我在写《闪灵》的报道”
And I said, "Can we talk to you?I write about The Shining."
他说：“真的吗？”
He said, "Really?"
他告诉我
This fellow told me
他接到了库布里克的电话 对方说：
that he got a phone call from Stanley Kubrick, who said,
“我想拍一部关于《闪灵》的电影
”"I think I want to make a movie about The Shining."
之后他们谈了很久
And then he would keep this fellow on the phone for a long time.
经理说：“我们谈了很多
He said, "We had many long, long conversations
他几乎把什么都跟我说了”
in which he picked my brain about everything."
他又说
And at that point, he said,
“库布里克计划来这里拍一部电影”
"Kubrick was talking about maybe coming here
而这正是他期待的
to make the movie here,"which I expect, at that point,
酒店经理喜欢这个想法 因为
that fellow liked the idea of,
这会让酒店更有名气
so it would make his hotel famous.
接着 库布里克说：“我要先让考察团去看看”
And Kubrick said, "I'd like to send out a research team."
接着考察团就来了...
And so he then sent out...
经理说 有两三个人
the man said it was something like two or three people
在酒店那儿住了
who came out here and stayed here
两三个月 到处拍照取景
for two or three months,taking photographs everywhere.
他们也花了很多时间研究丹佛
And they spent a lot of time also down in Denver
和科罗拉多州的历史
n the Colorado state archives,
他们理清了
finding out,as I would now expect,
科罗拉多州的历史
the full history of Colorado,
包括不同地方代表的旗帜
which... the flag of which plays a part.
还有淘金 科罗拉多淘金热
And the gold rush,the Colorado Gold Rush
也是相当大的事件
was also a very big event.
还有很多...
And there's all...there's still a lot
还有在科罗拉多州 白人、印第安人
of American Indian/white people tension in Colorado
和纳瓦霍人、阿拉帕霍人的对立
with Navajos and Arapahos just to the south.
这个调查团队找出了关于
This research team found out absolutely everything
科罗拉多 关于埃斯蒂斯公园
about Colorado,about Estes Park,
关于斯坦利酒店的一切一切
about the Stanley Hotel,about its entire history,
拍了各个地方的照片
took photographs all over the place.
我的印象中 这三个月就是
Three months was the impression that I have
他所描述的那样
of what he said about how this research team
收集了一切
gathered absolutely everything.
库布里克发掘了科罗拉多州的
Kubrick unearthed an enormous amount about the real history
大量历史事实
of Colorado, where this takes place,
他所做的是去发现一条
because what he has done is found a way to dig
探索我们文明的道路
into all of the patterns of our civilization,
探索我们的时代 我们的文化
our times and our cultures,
甚至那些我们不屑一顾的东西
and the things that we don't want to look at.
而这部电影也是关于
And this movie is very much also about denial
白人对大屠杀的否认
of the genocides that we committed...
欧洲白人
we white folk from Europe...
在此犯下罪恶
committed here and not that...
然而并不是只有白人进行了大屠杀
not that white folks are the only people who do genocide.
全人类都有过大屠杀 库布里克在电影中表达的很清楚
All humans do, as Kubrick makes clear in this movie.
他会将电影中出现的一切事物
He would research everything and the full history and nature
一切历史 自然 都调查清楚
of everything you're gonna see in the movie on the screen
之后将它们合为一体
and then boil it down and boil it down
形成一个普遍的 总体的模式
until he got the universal human and global patterns
这让电影更加真实
that make it so real.
- 白人的负担啊 劳埃德
- White man's burden,Lloyd, my man.
真是白人的负担
White man's burden.
我喜欢你 劳埃德
I like you, Lloyd.
我一直都喜欢你
I always liked you.
你一直是最棒的
You were always the best of 'em.
从延巴克图到缅甸州的波特兰
The best goddamned bartender
到俄勒冈州的波特兰
from Timbuktu to Portland, Maine,
你一直是最好的调酒师
or Portland, Oregon,for that matter.
- 谢谢你的承认
- Thank you for saying so.
- 这是什么意思？
- What does it mean?
杰克所说的 "从延巴克图开始
Jack saying, "You always were the best of 'em."
你一直是最棒的
Starting in Timbuktu?
作为一名作家 杰克从未去过延巴克图
Jack the schoolteacher was never in Timbuktu,
但作为普通人民
but Jack the universal weak male
曾被征兵参战的杰克
hired by armies to go commit atrocities
去过那儿
has always been there.
毫无疑问 "波特兰"是指
Now, of course,the word "Portland"
我们当时登陆的地方
is neat because it means where we landed
或者说是英国 欧洲人登陆的地方
or where the British or the Europeans landed.
而俄勒冈州的波特兰则指他们
And Portland, Maine... Oregon is where they may have taken off
去往远东的出发地
from to go further west.
库布里克考虑了
Kubrick is thinking about the implications
一切存在事物的涵义
of everything that exists.
美国伟大诗人理查德·威尔伯曾说
You know, the power of the genie is in its confinement,
鬼怪的力量存在于限制之中
as the great American poet Richard Wilbur said.
神灯里有一万年的精华
Boiling it down, you know,10,000 years in a little lamp,
你得赶快行动
you got to get your act together.
但那正是伟大艺术的来源
But that's the essence of great art.
就像梦一样
It's like a dream.
伟大艺术将一切熔在一个象征之中
It's boiled everything down to an emblematic symbol
熔出了生活
that's got all of life in it.
请允许我再拓展一下
Now, if you'll allow me to make a little bit of a link here.
最近我一直在思考一个问题
As I've thinking of this more in recent years,
我们所理解的就是我们梦想的本质
what we now understand to be the nature of what dreams are,
我是说 通常的理论是
I mean, it seems to be,the general theory is,
大脑将我们先前的经验
that it's a way for the brain to boil down
归纳 总结为一体
all of the previous experiences
再加上那一天的经历
and then add in that day's experiences
我们可以发现
as well to see what kind of overall universal patterns
希区柯克·《爱德华大夫》
一个普遍的模式
there are to be found,
这样你就会知道那个模式是什么样的
so that you can be aware of what the patterns are out there,
就可以在看到危险发生时
so that your subconscious will be all the more ready
或者在重要的事情发生时
to react suddenly when you see something dangerous happen
大致意思应该就是吃一堑长一智和应激
你可以提前作出反应
or something important happen that may lead you to a mate or to some food or away from danger.
因此 库布里克拍电影的方式
And therefore, the way Kubrick made movies was not unlike
就是根据这些理论的
the way, according to these current theories,
我们的大脑可以创造出记忆
our brains create memories and, for that matter, dreams.
这就是库布里克拍《闪灵》的基本原则
That's the ultimate shining that Kubrick does.
他就像有着巨型大脑
He is like a mega brain for the planet
能够将全世界的大量研究
who is boiling down with all of this extensive research,
和各种模式结合起来
all of these patterns of our world
之后还给我们一个梦一般的电影
and then giving them back to us in a dream of a movie...
因为电影就像梦一样...
because movies are like a dream...
所以我认为
and that's related to why I think
在电影《闪灵》中
there's a lot of evidence that what Kubrick
库布里克给了我们许多关于过去的证据
also gave us in The Shining is a movie about the past.
不是随随便便的过去
Not just any past.
过去
The past.
我是指历史性的
I mean past-ness.
这是一部关于过去所带来的冲击的电影
It's a movie about how the past impinges.
这也是鬼怪的含义
That's what ghosts are.
就像电影开头的诡异音乐
That's what those skitter-y voices in the opening shot
无形中追随着你
that are following are about.
当我想到《闪灵》时 通常用两个
There's two phrases from T.S.Eliot that I often think of
艾略特*所写的句子的来形容
when I'm thinking about The Shining.
*美国诗人
一个是"噩梦"...
One of them is "The night"...
我觉得应该都是艾略特的句子
I think they're both from T.S. Eliot...
历史噩梦...
The nightmare of history...
"我们如何从历史噩梦中醒来？"
"how can we awake from the nightmare of history?"
- 另一个词是...艾略特所说的...
- And the other is his phrase...T.S. Eliot's phrase...
"历史总是狡兔三窟"
"History has many cunning passages."
我认为这两句都直接而恰当的
And I think both of those phrases are directly apt
形容了《闪灵》 正如我们所见
for The Shining,in which we see
酒店和树篱迷宫里都有许多道路
many cunning passages in the maze and in the hotel itself
在那儿 过去成了噩梦
and in which the past becomes a nightmare,
库布里克向你展示了 如何通过
and in which Kubrick shows us how you escape
原路折返 逃离过去的噩梦
from the nightmare of the past by retracing your steps,
就像丹尼最后所做的
as Danny does in that last line,
这意味着 只有当你
which means acknowledging what happened
看清各种模式时
and learning about the past and then getting out,
你才知道如何避免
only if you are going to be able to shine
才能够去追寻美好的事物
and see what the patterns are
才能了解 掌握现实
so you know to get away from them
才能在过去中吸取经验
and avoid them and go for the good things.
我是说 《闪灵》是库布里克关于家庭分裂的电影
I mean, The Shining is his movie about how families break down,
不管他们是个体小家庭
whether they are an individual family
还是一个即将分裂的大家庭
or the larger societal family that tries to break up individual families.
他的最后一部电影 《大开眼界》则恰恰相反
And his lats movie,Eyes Wide Shut is the opposite.
它是关于家庭的痛苦尝试
It's about a family sorely tried,
比尔·哈特福特和他的妻子 儿女们
Bill Hartford and his wife and child,
成功抵制了各种根植在
that survives all the horrible temptations
我们基因中的诱惑
that are in our DNA.
走出迷宫
- 这就是我们著名的树篱迷宫
- This is our famous hedge maze.
这里很好玩
It's a lot of fun.
但我不想进去试试
But I wouldn't want to go in there
除非我有一个小时的时间 才能找到出口
unless I had an hour to spare to find my way out.
- 几年后可以租《闪灵》的光碟时
- I did not look at it again for a number of years
我才看了第二遍
until it came out in rental.
之后我又看了好几遍
And then I picked it up a couple of times.
那时候租一次碟可以看三天
And, what, you had three days in order to watch a rental?
所以我记得在那三天
And so, I can remember watching
看了一遍又一遍
it over and over again during those three days
每一遍都仔仔细细的看
and really taking a good look at it then.
当时我就像 "对 我记得这里
And I was able to think "Oh,yes, this is what I remember.
我本来以为是那样的"
This is what I thought I saw,"
然后捕捉到了更多的细节
and then catching more things.
而在看DVD之前 我都没有发现这些
But it wasn't, of course,until DVD came out
有了DVD之后 我可以坐下
that I was really able to sit down
认真的 完整的看这部电影
and take a good look at it as far as just running through it
一遍又一遍
over and over and over again.
库布里克将这些事物表现的
Kubrick presents these things where it's, you know, real...
更加真实
you know, it's realistic.
你不清楚真正发生的是什么
You're not supposed to see what's actually going on.
比如丹尼
You've got Danny.
他在游戏房里 然后转身
He's in the game room.He turns around.
我们的注意力应该在那两个女孩身上
We're supposed to be focused on the two girls there.
可是...我看见...在左边
And than you... I saw...over on the left,
我看到了那个滑雪者的海报
I see this skiing poster.
这里的细节是关于杰克的
And the thing is that you already have Jack.
杰克之前询问过能否滑雪
He's already asked about skiing.
但是...他当时说"能滑雪吗
But why isn't... you know,"What about skiing?
在酒店这儿可以滑雪吗？"
Isn't the skiing good here in the hotel?"
但他已经被告知为何滑雪不好
And he's already given the story of why it isn't good,
为何不能滑雪
why they can't do that.
但是 这里依然贴着滑雪海报
But you got the skiing poster.
我的眼神被拉了过去
And my eye is drawn to it.
我意识到 这不是一个滑雪者
And I realize that's not a skier.
这是...这是一个牛头人
That's a... that's a minotaur.
我注意到了它
It just leaped out at me.
后来我在录像带上
And so that was something
又仔细看了看
that I was able to look at later on VHS
之后说"没错 那儿就是一个牛头人"
and say, "Yes, I had actually seen a minotaur there,"
他的上半身 的确是
where the upper body, you've got this really, you know,
一个夸张的身体形态
overblown physique,very physical physique.
你注意到了一个细节...
And then you've got the suggestion...
就是那个滑雪杖
you have a suggestion of a skiing pole there,
但它并不在那
but it's not really there.
它只是一个暗示
It's just a suggestion of one.
它的下半身被固定
And the lower body is positioned,
双腿摆放的姿势
the way the legs are,
整体造型 都像是一个牛头人
it's like a minotaur,the build is.
而且尾巴也出现在图中
And you've actually got the tail there.
所以它就是一个牛头人
And so it is a minotaur.
在右边... 在门的另一边
And this is in...on the opposite side of the door
你可以看到骑在马背上的牛仔
you have a cowboy on a bucking bronco, so...
因此你可以看的出这是一种对应
and so you got a kind of echo there,
你在门的一边
where you got the
看到牛头人
minotaur on one side,the bull man,
而在另一边 是一个牛仔
and on the other side,you got the cowboy,
骑在野马身上的人
the man on the bucking bronco.
而这个场景是紧跟在
And this is just following the scene where they...
厄尔曼带着杰克和温迪
Ullman has been taking Jack and Wendy
穿过科罗拉多休息室
through the Colorado Lounge,
带领他们参观的那个场景之后
showing off the Colorado Lounge.
当他们进入大厅
And they go into the hall
在科罗拉多休息室的后面
behind the Colorado Lounge.
在这里的墙上
And what's there,but on the wall,
你可以看到一幅关于美国印第安人
there is a painting of an American Indian
带着水牛头饰的画
with a buffalo headdress on.
而在那时 厄尔曼在和温迪讨论
And at that point,Ullman is discussing with Wendy
哪些人曾经住过这家酒店
who has stayed there at the hotel.
名门望族 上流人士 璀璨之星
Royalty, the best people,stars have stayed there.
- 名门望族？
- Royalty?
- 都是最上等的人
- All the best people.
- 在海报底部 你可以看到"君主"这个词
- You have "monarch" on the bottom, which, you know,
这是皇室的核心词
keys in with royalty.
同样你也可以看到关于明星的暗示
And you also have this whole idea of the stars.
而君主的名字 应该是阿斯忒里俄斯*
And the minotaur's name is,what, Asterius?
*希腊神话里的国王
他名字的含义是"星光闪耀的"
His name is Asterius,which means "starry."
因此 你可以得到一些
So you know, you got several things there
关于神话的联系
to do with mythology that fit in.
这让我很兴奋
It's very exciting to me.
这是一种...一种
That was the... you know,that's the kind of
这是一种很刺激的感受
leap-up-end-down moment where you go,
"哇偶 看看库布里克做了些什么"
"Oh, wow, look at what Kubrick has there."
我知道 牛头人住在迷宫的核心地带
Yeah, I mean the minotaur lives at the heart of the labyrinth.
他是迷宫的一部分
He's a part of the labyrinth.
而迷宫 至少在神话中
The labyrinth,at least in the myth...
这个特殊的神话
you know,in this particular myth...
是为牛头人而打造的
was built for the minotaur.
这个酒店...就是一个迷宫
The hotel is... you know,it is the labyrinth.
而杰克就是那个牛头人
And Jack is the minotaur.
在一些场景里...
You have scenes with him where he...
他在...那叫啥？
such as in...what is it?
在 星期二 那个场景里
The Thursday scene.
冬雪初降
The snowfall has started.
温迪和丹尼在外面玩雪
You have Wendy and Danny outside playing.
杰克在科罗拉多休息室里
And Jack is inside the Colorado Lounge,
注视着外面的母子俩
and he's looking out at them.
脑袋略微下低 眼睛...
His head is tilted down,and his eyes are somewhat...
眼睛向上抬
his eyes are elevated.
它们在朝上看
They're pointing up.
然后他的眉毛向上弯曲
And his eyebrows are drawn up.
但他脸上的表情
But he has this expression on his face
脸上像公牛一样的表情 在电影中
that he gets progressively throughout the film
逐渐增多 形象起来
that is very bull-like.
这是很像牛头人的表情
It has a very minotaur-like expression.
这和库布里克在其他电影中
It's the same kind of expression that Kubrick
使用的表情 是一样的
pulls out in other films,
比如在电影《全金属外壳》中
such as it was on Private Pyle's face
浴室里狂暴的二等兵
in the berserker scene in the bathroom
派尔的脸上
in Full Metal Jacket.
《2001：太空漫游》
因此 这并不是《闪灵》所特有的
So it's, you know,not specific to this film.
《发条橙》
还有很多的牛头人和神话意象
There's more minotaur imagery and labyrinth imagery.
比如 在金色大厅中
There's the Gold Room.
在金色大厅的前段
In front of the Gold Room,
你可以看到"休息时间"的标志
you have the "Unwinding Hours" sign.
而这和迷宫是有联系的
And that plays in with the labyrinth,
我联想到...
where you have...
*希腊神话中的雅典国王
提修斯*进入迷宫
Theseus enters into the labyrinth,
那时他的身上带着线球
and he has the thread with him
系在自己身上
that he ties at the beginning that,
借助线球进入迷宫
you know, assists him in going through the labyrinth,
这样可以顺利的找到回路
where he can find his way back out.
所以当我看到"休息时间"的标志时
And so I see the "Unwinding Hours" sign
我觉得和那个线球有关系
as having to do with that thread.
我还注意到了那个棒球棒
For a while there,I was into baseball.
对球棒的研究又让我很兴奋
And I get very excited with baseball when I'm into baseball.
我可以做自己
You know, I can be by myself,
可以带我装逼带我飞
and I will be leaping up and down.
库布里克对我来说就像那样
And Kubrick is like that for me,
我看到那个牛头人海报
where all I have to do is see the minotaur poster there,
感叹道 "噢天哪 看这里！
"and I go, "Oh, my goodness.Look at this!"
因为一般人是看不到这个牛头人的
Because you're not supposed to see the minotaur.
- 影片中 丹尼骑着他的车逛酒店
- Danny is shown riding his big wheel
一共有三次
through the hotel three times.
第一次 我觉得是关于现实主义的
The first ride, I think, is about realism.
丹尼他...
That's Danny is a...
他在转圈
Danny is doing a loop around the lounge set.
他绕着服务台的走廊
You know, he goes through the service hallway
然后穿过休息室
and then he goes through the lounge
之后回到服务台的走廊
and then he goes back into the service hallway.
因此 当你第一次看这段
And, you know,when you first see the movie,
你会觉得 他只在闲逛
you're like,"He's just wandering around.
这很疯狂 但是...
It's crazy, it's just"...
但是...它很...
But it... no, it's very...
它只是一个简单的圆圈
it's just a very simple loop.
他绕了一圈
He does it once.
但是这让你对这个地方
But that gives you an idea of where...
有了初步的概念
of what that place is.
我是说 你了解到
I mean, you know,all right, you understand
这是个圆
that that set is real.
这是一个长镜头
You know, like,it's a continuous shot.
不会有花招
There are no tricks.
第二次骑车 是在六角走廊里
In the second ride,in the hexagonal hallway,
这里有很多...
there are a lot of...
有很多把戏
there are more tricks.
比如 他并没有继续绕圈
Like, he doesn't do a loop.
他的路线是钥匙形的
He does kind of like a key-shaped...
或者说是P形路线
you know, or a p-shaped loop around this hallway.
你可以看到这和休息室之间实际存在的联系
And you see the realism of the connection to the lounge set.
你也同样会发现电梯的虚假性
And... but you also see the fakery of the fake elevators.
你可以看到 只有一秒钟
And you see...for just one second,
角落边的有色玻璃大窗户
you see the big stained glass windows out of the corner,
在角落的框框里
in the corner of the frame
在丹尼绕着电梯转弯之前
right before he takes a turn around the elevator.
这是难以置信的 因为
Like, that's incredible because,
感觉那个窗户连接了走廊
like, that connects that whole hallway
和巨大的科罗拉多休息室
to the giant Colorado Lounge set.
我是说 就那一秒
I mean,that's just for one second.
其实 他们没必要这么设置
They didn't have to do that,you know?
但是 这是一种暗喻
But it's also... you know,it's a metaphor
因为丹尼的高度提高了
because he's also elevated.
他比之前的位置提高了一层
He's one level up from where he was before.
感觉就像 他在同一个地方开始 但是上了一层楼
Like, he starts in the same place, just one floor up,
在休息室的东北部
you know, in the northeast corner of the set.
因此 他现在处于东北角 而且比原来高了一层
So now he's in the northeast corner and one level up.
如果你把它看做是一个隐喻的话
And if you take it as a metaphor of, like,
这就像从普通的现实上升到了你脑中
going from a mundane reality to up into your head
一个更加虚、幻的现实
to more of a fantastical reality...
第三次骑车更加诡异
The third one is even stranger,
因为他从后勤部开始
'cause he starts off in the service unit.
还是同一个地方
He starts off in the same,
在休息室的东北角
you know, northeast corner of the lobby hall,
从后勤部的走廊出发
of the lobby service hallway.
然后他转弯 突然 他就在楼上了
And then he takes a turn,and suddenly he's upstairs
到了他们公寓的外面
in the area outside their apartment
所以 这就像是在前两次
So, like,it's a kind of a combination
他是在下面 而第三次他就到了楼上
of the first two,where like he's down low and then he's up high
接着他转了弯 然后他突然...
And then he takes a turn,and he's suddenly...
突然就到了黄蓝相间的墙纸那儿
he's in that that yellow,yellow and blue wallpaper.
我们称这里为服务台的走廊地区
Let's say that's in the service hallway area.
现在 他在父母房间的外面
He's, you know, right outside his parents' bedroom,
因此 在骑车和幻觉之间
so there's this connection between him
有所关联
going on these big wheel rides and dreaming.
就像他在自己卧室旁边
Like, he's near his bedroom.
他在...我们知道他的父母在楼下工作
He's near... like, you see his parents are working downstairs,
但是现在他在楼上
but he's upstairs.
就像我们看到他的母亲在打电话
You know, like, you see his mom on the telephone,
而他在飞快的骑车
and then he's flying.
他骑到了位于她工作地点
He goes above her to the bedroom,
上方的卧室
which is above where she's working,
就像骑在位于他爸爸工作地点的上方
just as the hexagonal hallway
那条六角走廊里
is above where his dad is working.
所以他的三轮车成了探索父母脑海
So these big wheel rides become like a visionary way
虚幻的工具
of Danny to explore his parents' headspace.
而237房间
You know, like,room 237 is his, like...
就像他父亲的幻想密室
that's his father's fantasy chamber
他在那儿碰到了女巫
where, like, he gets it on with the witches.
那对双胞胎就像他母亲的幻想...
And the twins are like his mother's fantasy...
他母亲的幻想空间 她们就像
fantasy headspace where, like,they're these double blue women
这对想和丹尼一直玩下去的女人
who want to play with Danny forever and ever.
- 我们会过的很开心的
- We're all gonna have a real good time.
- 我对《闪灵》的理解是
- My interpretation of The Shining
这部电影有许多层面
is that there's many levels to this film.
就像一个三维的国际象棋
This is like three-dimensional chess.
而导演试着告诉我们一些看似分离
And he's trying to tell us several stories
却有着密切联系的故事
that appear to be separate but actually are not.
他也通过电影脚本来实现这一点
And he's doing this both through the overt script that he wrote.
他利用商业技巧来表达
He's telling it through tricks of the trade,
通过潜意识的和大量重复的影像
the subliminal imagery and these constant retakes,
和一些独特的视角 道具等来吸引你
giving him odd angles and things.
而他通过对
And he's also telling you
史蒂芬·金小说的改动 来让你感受到不同
through the changes that he made to the Stephen King novel.
*小说 剧本 电影
因此 如果你将这三者*结合
So if you watch those three things,
你会对电影有更深的了解
you begin to understand this deeper story.
而这个蕴含着着库布里克想法的
And this deeper story has its birth, I guess,
更深层次的故事
in the idea that Stanley Kubrick
我认为和阿波罗登月造假有关
was involved with faking the Apollo moon landings.
事实上 我主张 某种程度上 《2001：太空漫游》
In fact, I contend that 2001: A Space Odyssey,
是为了阿波罗影像的需要
in part, was a research and development project
而研究 发展的项目
for the Apollo footage that was shot.
我并不是说我们从未上过月球
I'm not saying we didn't go to the moon.
我是指 我们所看到的 是假的
I'm just saying that what we saw was faked
我们被库布里克蒙骗了
and that it was faked by Stanley Kubrick.
60到70年代的好莱坞
And I've had Hollywood special effects people
前屏特效专家告诉我
from the '60s and '70s who were front-screen projection experts
我完全揭露除了阿波罗登月影像
tell me that I absolutely have nailed the Apollo footage
是视频特效的结果
as being the result of front-screen projection.
只要浏览任何阿波罗的页面
Just go to any Apollo site and look,
你都会发现 他们挡住了视频的底部
and you'll see that they have to hide the bottom of the screen.
你在每一个阿波罗的影像 照片中
And you can always see the set/screen separation line
你总能看到菜单和视频之间的分界线
in every Apollo footage,every Apollo image,
视频影像总有一个背景
and the video footage that has a background.
研究者理查德·霍格兰
And Richard Hoagland,the researcher,
调查了阿波罗登月的照片
has looked into the Apollo imagery.
他找出了各种各样的问题
And he has found all sorts of problems with it
比如在宇航员周围的天空里
because in the sky around the astronauts,
他发现了灯光的反射和其他东西的折射
he's found reflecting lights and refracting things and...
一种舢板船几何形的物体
kind of a junk and geometry of things that are in the sky.
但他也错误地总结出
And he concluded, wrongly,
太空里有玻璃制成的巨大外星城市
that there are gigantic alien cities made out of glass.
他觉得自己看到的是玻璃屏幕上
What he's really seeing is the reflections of light
细小玻璃粉的反光
of the tiny beads on the scotch light screen
而那块玻璃是用来前屏的投影转换处理的
which is being used in the front-screen projection process.
并且 我仔细研究过阿波罗影像资料的
And so, once I nailed the front-screen projection process
前屏的投影转换
inside the Apollo footage,
然后我对库布里克是否在他后来的作品里
then I became interested in seeing if Kubrick left any clues
留下过任何关于阿波罗登月
in the rest of his career to his possible involvement
是自己造假的线索 产生了兴趣
in faking the Apollo moon footage.
而大概在两年前 当我收到
And I was overjoyed about two years ago
《闪灵》的蓝光碟时 我乐坏了
when I received my Blue-Ray copy of The Shining.
我用蓝光机播放了它
And I put it in my Blue-Ray machine
坐下看了一整夜
and sat down one night to watch it.
我想象了任何库布里克可能使用过的
And I realized that all of the things that one could imagine
关于阿波罗登月视频影像
that Stanley Kubrick would have had to go through
造假的事物
to fake the Apollo moon footage...
而在电影中
and there in the movie,
每一次库布里克对史蒂芬金的小说有所改动
every time that Stanley deviated from the Stephen King novel,
他也会加入一些新的问题
he deviated into those exact questions.
比如 与美国政府打交道的感觉
You know, what was it like to make a deal
是什么样的？
with the U.S. Government?
无意间透露了自己正在做的事情
What was it like to accidentally tell someone what you were doing
然后看着人们取笑你的不诚实
and to watch them possibly have to suffer the consequences
这种感觉是什么样的？
of your lack of integrity?
欺骗自己的妻子
What was it like to lie to your wife
为自己的言行不一找借口
and tell her that you were doing one thing
这种感觉是什么样的？
when you were doing another?
而当妻子发现你暗地里在做的事情时
What was it like when your wife found out
这种感觉又是什么样的？
what you were really doing?
这些问题就是在我八九年之后
These are the questions that I had long before
再看《闪灵》时
I had seen The Shining again
所想知道的
after a maybe an eight...or nine-year absence.
我在电影的前一个小时里 并没有找到答案
And I didn't... wasn't sure I was right for the first hour.
我不知道自己是否...
I wasn't sure that I had actually...
是否模糊了
you know, I wasn't sure if I was blurring the line
自己想看到的和正在看的
between what I wanted to see and what I was seeing.
而在电影的58分钟
And then at about 58 minutes in the film
是丹尼在玩玩具车时的那个著名场景
is the famous scene where Danny's playing with his trucks,
然后他站了起来
and he stands up
而他当时穿的毛衣上 印着
and he's wearing the Apollo 11 sweater
即将升空的阿波罗十一号
with the rocket taking off.
我知道自己捕捉到了它
Then I knew I'd nabbed it.
之后 我带着热情 继续看这部电影
And then I started watching the film with an intensity
就当从未看过一样
that I don't think I'd ever watched a movie before,
然后发现每一句台词都显得真实
and every line began ringing true.
比如 "温迪 这真像你做出的事
You know, "Wendy, that is just so typical of you.
你难道...你难道不知道
Don't you... don't you know
我要尽到一个员工的职责吗？
I have obligations to my employers?
你知道协议是什么意思吗?
Do you have any idea what a contract is?
你知道合同是什么意思吗？"
Do you know what an agreement is?"
杰克·尼克尔森（应该说杰克·托伦斯）对妻子的的长篇大论
Jack Nicholson's whole tirade against his wife...
这是史丹利
that's Stanley.
这是史丹利在告诉前妻 在他们离婚后
That's Stanley telling his wife that after she discovered
自己正在忙活的 是在制作阿波罗等于影像
what he was doing,which was the Apollo footage.
库布里克曾说 在所取景的酒店的请求下
他将原作中的“217房间”改为了“237房间”
由于酒店的确有217号房间
他们担心顾客看过《闪灵》之后 不敢入住
林 线 酒 店
胡德山 俄勒冈州
不 这不是真的
No, that's actually not true.
如果你打给度假酒店
If you call the Mount Hood Resort
预订217房间
and you ask for room 217
你会被告知 没有这间客房
you will find there is no such room.
因此 库布里克说的是假的
So that's just not true.
那个说法是假的
That statement's not true.
所以...
And so what...
史丹在说谎
Stanley was lying.
从217改为237并不是
Its not the reason that he changed the room number
那个原因
from 217 to 237.
他这么做
The reason that he changed it from 217 to 237
是因为 电影中的237房间...
was because the room,room 237 in the film is...
代表了他所在的登月工作室
represents the moon landing stage where he worked.
而关于月球 科学教材里说到...
And the moon, the standard science textbook said...
并且现在也这么说...
and they still say...
尽管现在有了激光测距 我们可以更精确
but now with lasers, we've gotten a little better reading.
但是...书上写到 月球
But... is that the mean distance of the moon
到地球之间的距离 刚好是237,000英里
from the earth is exactly 237,000 miles.
因此 他做出这样的改变是为了让你认识到
So he changed that so that you would understand
这是一间月舍
that this was the moon room.
因此 当丹尼站起来
So Danny stands up.
他穿着阿波罗十一号的毛衣
He's got the Apollo 11 sweater on.
开始走向237房间
He begins walking down the hallway towards room 237.
在门锁上 插着钥匙
And there's a key in the lock.
在钥匙上...
And on the key are...
写着词语"房间"和"不"
is the words "room" and then the word "n-o,"
英语里 "号"的缩写是"不"
which is an old acronym for "number."
因此这是237房间
So "room number 237,"
除此之外 钥匙上的大写字母分别是
except that the only capital letters on the key
R-O-O-M 和N-O里的N
are r-o-o-m and then the "n" from the acronym n-o.
而此时 你所能想到的带这些字母的单词
And if there's only two words that you can come up with
只有两个
that have those letters in 'em.
那就是"月亮"和"房间"
And that's "moon" and "room."
因此钥匙上写着的就是"月亮屋"
And so on the key, the tag,it says "moon room."
就是月舍了
And that is the moon room.
这就是一切都会发生的地方
This is where everything happens,
但不能是真实的
and none of it's real.
它们必须被谎言掩盖
And it all has to be lied about.
库布里克不能让人知道237房间
And he can't let anyone know what's really going on
到底发生了什么
in room 237.
此外 电影中还有很多对原作
And there's many, many other deviations from the book
改动的地方
to the movie.
- 这是真的
- It isn't real.
- 这些改动让史蒂芬·金抓狂了
- The deviations drove Stephen King out of his mind.
这么多年来 他一直痛骂《闪灵》
He just ranted and ranted for years
咆哮着有多痛恨它
how much he hated The Shining.
他痛恨是因为 他给了库布里克
And he hated it because he'd given Kubrick
如此好的拍摄题材
all this great source material
但他却丢弃了
and Kubrick threw it out.
而这最好的证明就是
And the whole idea of this is best exemplified
迪克·哈洛伦在高速上开车的场景
by the scene where Dick Hallorann  is driving up the highway,
暴风雪中 开往远望酒店的路上
trying to get to the Overlook during a winter storm
他路过了一起车祸
and he passes a wreck.
车祸现场是一辆挂车
And in the wreck,a semi has crashed
压在一辆红色的大众轿车上面
and crushed a red Volkswagen.
这是一个库布里克向史蒂芬发出的直接信息
And this is a direct message from Kubrick to King,
因为在小说中
because in the novel,
杰克·托伦斯的车是红色大众
Jack Torrance's car is a red Volkswagen.
但是在电影里 却是黄色大众
But in the movie,it's a yellow Volkswagen.
库布里克这是在对史蒂芬·金说
And what Kubrick is saying in that scene
**大爷
is a big "F you"to Stephen King.
他在说 这是老子的车
He's saying,This is my vehicle.
"我已经把你的车撞飞了
"I have wrecked your vehicle.
世人见证 我将你打败
And everybody in the world can see it.'
这让史蒂芬炸毛
And this drove King crazy.
理应如此
And it should have.
但现实所发生的
But what was really going on
以及关于这一切可以让人联想的
and what is just much more deliciously fascinating
事实上 是在表达
about all of this is that, in fact,
库布里克 打着拍摄史蒂芬金小说的幌子
Kubrick was faking the making of the Stephen King novel
实际上是在泄露关于他制造
in order to reveal the idea of what he went through
阿波罗登月影像的经历
to do the Apollo moon footage.
通往墓地的电梯
- 我认为 库布里克是一个
- My argument,as far as Kubrick goes,
观察力逆天的小孩
is that he was a preternaturally observant child.
他一直在观察
He read omnivorously.
他一直都去电影院
He went to movies all the time.
我相信 如果你看三十 四十年代的电影
And I think if you're going to movies and reading in the 1930s
你会发现你看到的都是关于
and the 1940s, a lot of what you're seeing and reading
希特勒 纳粹以及战争题材的
is Hitler and the Nazis and the war.
因此 作为一个敏锐的小孩 他对这些一定很敏感
So as a sensitive kid, he must have been alive to these things.
我不认为他曾忽略过这些
And I don't think he ever forgot anything, and this is...
所以他的电影内容丰富
which is why his films are so rich.
- 小猪 小猪
- Little pigs, little pigs,
让我进去
let me come in.
不要啰嗦 不要说话
Not by the hair on your chinny-chin-chin?
我吹 我吹 我用力的吹
Then I'll huff and I'll puff...
- 吹倒你的屋子吃了你
- And I'll blow your house in!
- 《三只小猪》
- Well,The Three Little Pigs,
我是说 我不记得...
I mean, I don't remember...
这也许是杰克·尼克尔森
That might have been one of the things
诸多临场发挥的场景之一
that Jack Nicholson might've ad-libbed initially.
库布里克是即兴发挥的虔诚者
Kubrick was a great believer in that.
但就算这是临场发挥 我觉得
But even if it was,I think the selection
对那段儿歌的选择
of that particular little rhyme
是非常适合当时氛围的
certainly fits in with the time periodization
我的意思是说
I've just been talking about,
当库布里克在这个场景里
because Kubrick would've run across that
联想到了在1933年（应是1934年）
when he saw The Three Little Pigs
获得奥斯卡最佳动画的电影 《三只小猪》
as an Academy Award winning cartoon in 1933.
电影诞生在那个特殊的时期
And so it comes out of that period.
因此 在三十年代 狼的意象
And so the whole idea of a wolf,which, during the 1930s,
渐渐从它本身作为
gradually transformed itself in popular mythology
大萧条时期 人所皆知的
and popular culture from being a symbol
饥饿 欲望的符号
of want and of hunger in the Great Depression
转变成了敌人的象征
into a symbol of enemies;
敌人 敌国
Enemy nations,enemy peoples,
军事侵略
military aggression.
当然 这也反映了 法西斯和纳粹
And of course, this reflects the rise of fascism
在欧洲的崛起
and Nazis in Europe.
但是 门前的狼
But initially,the wolf at the door
最开始是讽刺以及反犹太的象征
was an anti-Semitic stereotype and caricature
一开始 狼伪装自己
that... initially the wolf wears a disguise.
而背景音乐明显是
And the background music
东欧的犹太人演奏的乐曲
is clearly Eastern European sort of klezmer
或是意第绪音乐
or Yiddish music.
而在三十年代 这是一个典型的
And it's a classic example
迪士尼动画反犹太的例子
of early 1930s Walt Disney anti-Semitism.
所以我认为 在《三只小猪》中
So I think there are layers of meaning
有着多层含义
in The Three Little Pigs."
*奥地利犹太心理学家、精神病医师
此外 库布里克相信弗洛伊德*学说
And since Kubrick was a Freudian
我们也知道 他在《闪灵》的剧本中
and we know that he used Freudian work
使用了弗洛伊德的研究成果
in doing the screenplay for The Shining...
比如 布鲁诺·贝托尔海姆*的著作《童话的魅力》...
Bruno Bettelheim's The Uses of Enchantment...
*美国心理学家
这是弗洛伊德学派对童话意义的分析
and it's a Freudian analysis of the meaning of fairy tales.
在《闪灵》中 当他们频繁的引用
And in The Shining,we can see the fruits of that
*德国童话
《糖果屋历险记》*时 我们可以看到其成果
when they're constantly making references to Hansel and Gretel.
- 我感觉我每次到这 都要在身后
- I feel like I'll have to leave a trail of bread crumbs
丢下面包屑才行
every time we come in here.
浴缸里的巫婆 小孩被炙烤等等
- The witch in the oven and children being burned
这些应该都是
and so forth,which of course,
对大屠杀的暗示
is also perhaps, suggestive when it comes to the Holocaust.
血涌应该是几个恐怖场景之一
- The blood is one of the main ghosts
甚至是这部电影中
and perhaps the overarching ghost,
最重要的一个场景
in a certain sense,in this movie.
我们第一次看到血涌是在电影的开头
We first see it when Danny,at the beginning of the movie,
当丹尼在丹佛或者博尔德的公寓里
is at the sink in the little apartment
水槽的旁边
down in Denver or Boulder or wherever it is.
托尼在和丹尼交谈
And he's talking to Danny,
"你为什么不想去那儿?"
"Why don't you want to go there?"
接着突然 丹尼给他看了血涌
And then suddenly Danny shows him blood.
后来我们知道
And as we learn a little bit later,
远望酒店是于1907到1909年之间建在
the Overlook was built on the Indian burial ground
印第安坟地上的
between 1907 and 1909.
- 1907年开始建造
- Construction started in 1907.
1909年竣工
It was finished in 1909.
这个地方是
The site is supposed to be located
印第安人的墓场
on an Indian burial ground,
我也相信 他们在建造时
and I believe they actually had
击退过一些印第安人的攻击
to repel a few Indian attacks as they were building it.
- 因此 我们可以想象出
- So presumably,we can imagine the elevator
电梯是可以下降到印第安人的
shaft sinks down into the very bodies of the Indians,
坟地里的
so to speak.
这也就是涌血的出处了
And that's where the blood is coming from;
是印第安人的血
Literal blood of the Indians.
除了别的之外 这也是一部关于
And this movie is a movie about,among other things,
血肉筑城的国家的电影
the blood on which nations are built;
没错 是关于有着
Certainly the United States,
印第安人大屠杀历史的美国的
with the genocide of the American Indians.
但不仅仅这样
But it's not only that.
这也是库布里克那说个不停的暗示
This is a complete metaphor for what Kubrick is on about,
因为电梯的门一直是关着的
because the elevator's doors remain closed.
用其他的话说 这就是
In other words,it's as if it's like a symbol
压抑
of the repression.
我们不愿承认
We don't want to admit to it.
尽管我们说这是压抑
But in spite of our attempting to stay repressed about it,
*中世纪英国诗人
就像乔叟*说的
blood will out,murder will out,
其实就是纸包不住火的意思...
笺草难御火 吾血终横流
as Chaucer says in one of his tales.
所以血从边缘中被挤压出
And so the blood comes squeezing out from the side
淹没了我们
and overwhelms us.
接着在电影中它一次又一次的出现
And it keeps recurring over and over through the movie.
它...
And it's...
在影片的最后 温迪
And finally Wendy, when,at the very end of the movie,
她开始看到了鬼怪
she starts seeing ghosts.
她看到了血涌
She sees the blood.
这是我们普遍共同点的象征
It's the symbol of what we all have in common.
电影里还有很多
And there's lots of symbols in here
关于人类共性的符号
of what all humans have in common.
- 数字42在其它方也出现过
- 42 shows up in other places.
温迪和丹尼在酒店的电视上
Wendy and Danny watch The Summer of '42
*英文名中有数字"42"
这一段貌似欧洲版也被剪了
在看《往事如烟》*
on a hotel television.
此外 还有许多
And there are a number of other
关于这个数字的暗示
little references to that number.
停车场上有42辆轿车/货车{
联系整部电影 库布里克
And it's within a larger context
使用了许多有关联的数字
that Kubrick uses involving numbers in The Shining.
它们都是7的倍数
And they're all multiples of seven.
酒店建于1907年
The hotel was built in 1907.
在电影最后 杰克合影留念的派对
The party in which Jack is pictured at the end of film
在1921年7月举办
occurred in 1921 in July,
那一年的第七个月
the seventh month of the year.
这些与7相关的数字 我认为
These multiples of seven,I think,
反映出一个事实
also reflect the fact
that Kubrick was aware of the importance
那就是库布里克知道托马斯曼*
*德国作家
1924年的小说 《魔山》的的重要性
of Thomas Mann's novel of 1924,The Magic Mountain,
一部关于一所造在高山上的疗养院的小说
which similarly concerns a sanitarium...
尽管不是酒店 但很相似
though not a hotel...high up in the mountains.
托马斯·曼使用7这个数字
And Mann uses the number 7 there as a matter,
德语:魔山
作为一个符号 来象征危险命运
a symbol of the sort of dangerous fate
一步步靠近欧洲
that seems to have been stalking Europe lately.
在小说《洛丽塔》中 纳博科夫使用42
And in the novel Lolita,Nabokov uses the number 42
来作为亨伯特的命运和偏执病的象征
as a symbol of fate and Humbert's paranoia,
来表达他画地为牢的生活状态
the idea that he is constantly being tracked and that his life is doomed.
尽管库布里克在电影《洛丽塔》中
And even though Kubrick,in his film of Lolita,
只在酒店房间的门上
only uses the number once,
饶有趣味地使用了一次数字42
interestingly enough on a hotel room door,
我觉得从某种程度上来说
I think at some level of consciousness,
库布里克一直在模仿纳博科夫
Kubrick was always also drawing from Nabokov's use
对那个特殊数字的使用
of that particular number
将它作为一种危险 怨恨 甚至一种灾难
as a symbol of danger and malevolence and disaster.
- 影片开始时的背景乐取自安魂曲中
- The opening sound is from the great funeral mass,
末日经唱段 意思是审判日
Dies Irae,which is the day of judgment,
曲中宣称 "葬礼即将到来
which announces,"This is going to be a funeral.
这会是全人类的审判日"
This is going to be about a judgment on the human race."
这是关于过去的
It's about the past.
但我记得
But I think I remembered
我对开场的印象
that my impression from the opening scene
那段航拍的镜头
in which that astonishing helicopter shot
让我感到毛骨悚然
gives you a totally creepy feeling.
你正欣赏着美丽的自然风光
You're looking at great,beautiful nature,
但你感觉你在追随着什么
but you know you're following something.
你就像...
You're, like, flying along
在一辆渺小汽车的上空 追着它飞
on top of this little,tiny, insignificant car.
尽管没有写出这段镜头的拍摄者
It's the ultimate point of view shot
但它是非常极致的画面展现
without telling you who the point of view is.
如果你想暂停然后思考
If you want to stop and think about it,
你会想 "这是一段航拍镜头"
you think,'This is a helicopter shot"
但对于普通观众来说
But for the general audience,
你只会觉得自己就像一个游魂
all you know is that you are like a ghost.
你像一个天使
You are like an angel.
你就像一个
You are like something
有着超能力的神奇飞侠
that flies with supernatural abilities
览尽这个星球的风光
across the landscape of the planet.
还有那飞掠而过的声音...
And the soundtrack had that skittering...
我没有办法模仿出来
I can't imitate it...
但是那个声音听起来就像...
but that skittering music that sounded to me...
我第一次看这部电影就有这种感觉...
and I was conscious of this the first time I saw the movie...
就像历史之声在耳畔回荡
like the thousands of voices from the past.
就像桃乐丝·赛儿丝
"The cloud of witness,"as the phrase is in...
某篇文章的标题：云之证人
Dorothy Sayers uses it as the title for some story.
云之证人 史之幽灵
The cloud of witness,all the ghosts from the past;
我不知道
And I didn't know.
这些簇拥的声音是来自
Were these the voices of the many crowds
外星人 还是鬼怪...
of aliens or of ghosts or...
我不知道
I didn't know what.
但那飞掠的 尖锐的声音
But already that skittering, high music
伴随着穿过湖面
with that follow shot across the lake
穿过汽车的那个镜头
and then across the car itself,
让我背后发毛
it was the ultimate in spooky
因为你感觉这辆车正被跟踪着
because you had the feeling this car is being followed
而它并不知道我们在跟踪它
and it doesn't know it,and we're following it.
我是说 我可以用象征派的观点
I mean, I could go on for a long time
带着对《闪灵》的尊重
about the symbolism of that
对此津津乐道
with regard to what The Shining really is.
而我们对《闪灵》的理解
And The Shining,as we come to understand it,
是看到历史的丰富以及
is seeing through all the layers of history
历史的恐惧
and the horrors of history,
在那个回顾的场景中
even autobiographically in that scene
格雷迪和杰克在血红色的男士卫生间里
where Grady and Jack talk in the blood-red men's room
格雷迪说 "你儿子很有天赋
and Grady says, "Your son has a very great talent.
我不认为你意识到其天赋之高
\MI don't think you realize how great it is.
但他是个调皮的小孩"
He's a very willful boy."
接着杰克说 "是的 他很调皮..."
And Jack says, "Yes, he is..."
- 顽皮的熊孩子
- A very willful boy.
- 托伦斯先生 你是否知道
- Did you know, Mr. Torrance,
你儿子试图带领一个外人
that your son is attempting to bring an outside party
到这个派对里
into this situation?
- 这就是老库
- That's Kubrick.
他所做的就是将观众和人性
What he's trying to do is bring the audience
带入这部电影
and humanity into this situation.
在电影里 他试图让我们理解
In this movie, he is trying to get through to us all...
让在电影院里看这部电影的人明白
the human race in the movie theaters watching this...
我们虽然存在 但是我们看不到
that we are doing these things but don't see it,
我们在一遍又一遍地
that we are committing these horrendous things
犯着可怕的错误 然后忘记
over and over again and then forgetting them...
这一点他在电影中
which is... of course,he represents many, many times in the movie...
通过让角色似懂非懂然后忘记的方式
by having characters seem to know something
表达了许多次
and then not know it and forget it.
- 你把你的妻子和女儿剁成了肉末
- You, uh, chopped your wife and daughter up into little bits.
- 可我一点都回想不起来了
- I don't have any recollection of that at all.
- 这就像人性
- That's like the human race.
我们犯下罪恶然后遗忘
We commit atrocities and then forget it.
- 比尔 这是杰克·托伦斯
- Bill, I'd like you to meet Jack Torrance.
你好
- How do you do?
- 你好 比尔
- Bill, how do you do?
- 见到你很高兴
- It's nice to meet you.
- 我也是
- It's a pleasure to meet you.
- 有些人认为电影中
- Some people think that,
并不是所有的面试都是真实的
like, not all of the interview is real.
有一些是杰克对于面试场面的幻想
Some of it is Jack's imagination or fantasy of what the interview would be like.
比如 比尔·沃森衣服的变化
Like, also, Bill Watson's clothes change.
条纹的
纯色的
他的裤子变了样
Like,his pants change patterns.
同样诡异的是
And what's also weird is,
他*在《耶稣基督万世巨星》*里还扮演了彼拉多**
he plays Pontius Pilate in Jesus Christ Superstar.
*比尔·沃森的扮演者
*2001年英国电影
**钉死耶稣的古代罗马犹太总督
-  ♪ 钉死他 ♪
- ♪ Crucify him ♪
♪ 钉死他 ♪
♪ Crucify him ♪
♪ 钉死  钉死 钉死  ♪
♪ Crucify, crucify, crucify ♪
- 演的是个大反派
- Really playing against type
这也是一种暗示
and just being this sort of cipher.
我的意思是 某种程度上他是杰克的另一面
I mean, in a way he's,he's kind of Jack's double
有点儿像《大开眼界》中的
kind of in the same way that Bill Hartford has a double
比尔·哈特福特
in Eyes Wide Shut.
他走进那个父亲刚去世的
You know, he goes to that blonde woman's house
金发美女的家里
whose father just died
而他的未婚夫看起来十分像汤姆·克鲁斯
and her fiancé looks exactly like Tom Cruise,
他们有着一样的发型
has the same haircut.
- 我一直都记得比尔·沃森 那个小助手...
- I've always thought that Bill Watson, the little assistant...
我说小 是指相比于厄尔曼
and by little, I mean that he's sort of a shrunken figure...
比尔·沃森被叫来后 坐在那儿
to Ullman, who's brought in and sits there
看起来严厉 忿恨而安静
looking sort of dour and resentful and quiet
他的肤色是有点儿...
and whose skin color is sort of a half...
不是白的
it's not white.
有点儿偏棕
It's sort of toward brown.
我一直觉得他代表着屈服...
I've always thought that he sort of represents a subdued...
比赛中的输家
somebody from a subdued race.
当厄尔曼问"你能帮他们整理一下行李吗？"时
He seems a little bit diffident when Ullman says,
他看起来有点变化
"Will you go collect their luggage?"
他说"好吧"
He says, "Fine."
- 好吧
- Fine.
- 而他们在参观酒店时
- And as they're given the tour around all the hotel,
比尔·沃森一直跟在后面
Bill Watson is always trailing behind,
就像一个给人干杂活的管家
like somebody who's going to be a little factotum to go get things.
我一直觉得他也许代表了
I've always thought he sort of maybe represented,
优势条件下的傲慢文化
you know, the condition in the dominant arrogant culture
就像当时的印第安人
that the Indians had at that time.
- 他是政府的无声监护人
- He is the silent guardian for the government.
斯图尔特厄尔曼则代表了美国政府的外在形象
Stewart Ullman represents the face of the U.S. government.
因此库布里克让他戴了假发
And that's why Kubrick gave him the toupee
让他看起来更像肯尼迪总统
that makes him look like John F. Kennedy.
我认为比尔·沃森
And I think that he is the guy
是一个默默注视着一切的人...就像
who's silently watching everything and, you know...
中央情报局
CIA, I guess.
或者国家安全局
Kind of NSA guy.
而他很有可能代表了
And he probably represents
这个房间 即远望酒店的
the real managers of the house,
真正管理员 而巴里尼尔森则是...
of the Overlook,and Barry Nelson is the...
一个公关形象
just the person that's out in front.
- 比尔什么也不说
- He doesn't say a thing.
他是酒店的看门人
He's the summer caretaker.
对我而言他就像
And he seems to me
和温迪在某种程度上达成了一致
to have certain correspondences with Wendy.
杰克在酒店里不怎么干活儿
Jack really doesn't work around the hotel.
而温迪则一直忙里忙外
Wendy gets in there,and she does all the work.
- 你肯定会有一种感觉...
- You do get the feeling that he's going...
那就是杰克即将替代他
that Jack's going to be doing his work,
因为他看起来对杰克有些怀疑
because he seems a little,like, leery of Jack.
我曾经面试过很多次
Like, I've been in job interviews,
而我总会发现 副面试官
and I've always found that that second person
才是真正面试你的人
they call in is,like, the person you're actually interviewing for.
他像是在做一个决定
He's making the decision,like, that silent person,
那种注视...
that, like...kind of, like, glare...
斜眼注视着你
like, squints at you.
在被要求帮杰克搬行李时 他叹了口气
Yeah, and he sighs when he's asked to move Jack's luggage.
- 比尔 可以把托伦斯的东西
- Bill, would you have the Torrances' things
搬到他们的房间里吗
brought to their apartment?
- 好吧
- Fine.
书中的照片
- 这里有一个从广角场景淡入的叠化
- There's a dissolve which fades from a wide shot
出现了最后那张黑白照片
of the, you know,final black-and-white photo
接着是杰克脸部的特写
to a close-up of Jack's face.
而这里大概有一秒
And just for a second there,
当杰克的头发叠化出了希特勒的胡子
his hairline fades in to form a Hitler moustache.
- 我觉得在这么多年里 在这家酒店里
- I think a lot of things happened right here
发生了很多事
in this particular hotel over the years
而且不全是好事
and not all of 'em was good.
- 他曾问到
- He once said,
"你怎么样才能把这么多东西"...
"How do you get all of that"...
就是大屠杀
meaning the Holocaust...
"拍成一部两个小时的电影的?"
"into a two-hour movie?"
我认为 库布里克觉得大屠杀是如此的
I think he found the Holocaust of such evil magnitude
罪恶 以至于他不能让自己
that he just couldn't bring himself
正确的看待他
to treat it directly,
因此他使用了恐怖片的形式
which is why he used the form of a horror film
来间接的表现它
to treat it indirectly.
我认为 库布里克有意识的
- I believe Kubrick,possibly consciously,
解决了一个历史问题 那就是
has solved a kind of problem that history has,
为什么人们对过去的大屠杀
which is that it's very hard for many people
很难在情感上
to connect emotionally to a gigantic big killing
有所沟通
we hear about in the past.
那些没有切身体验的人
People who don't have direct family experience
听到的只有数字
of it themselves may hear the statistic.
希特勒 光是在大屠杀中
You know, Hitler,among other things,
就屠杀了六百万的犹太人
killed 6 million Jews in his Holocaust.
六百万是一个太大的数字
6 million's a number too big.
斯大林曾有一句名言
I mean Stalin is reputed to have said, you know,
"杀一个人是犯罪和悲剧
"You kill one person,it's a murder and a tragedy.
杀一百万人 就只是数据了"
You kill a million people,it's a statistic."
他阐述了一个心理学事实
He was talking about a psychological fact.
而你知道 斯大林他自己...
And, you know, Stalin himself was... what is it...
在三十年代 乌克兰西部
starved about 3 million people
也有意的饿死了三百万人
in the western Ukraine in the '30s on purpose.
我认为 库布里克可能意识到
My point is it may be that Kubrick
自己提供了一条可以让我们
was conscious of having offered a kind of way to bridge
感受到庞大数字的桥梁
that inability to feel for those gigantic statistics in that,
如果你第一次去看《闪灵》
if you go and see The Shining innocent the first time
同时感到害怕 恐惧
and are terrified...you're just terrified
然后 你会记住这种感觉...
and you'll always remember being terrified...
会意识到这部电影的象征意义和
and then go back aware of what the symbolism
更深层次的含义
and the general larger pattern meanings of the movie are,
之后你就会思考其中的联系
then you can begin to make something of a connection,
你就会说 "哦天哪"
saying, "Oh, my God."
我还记得丹尼和温迪
I remember being terrified
独处场景时的恐惧感
for the individual little Danny and Wendy here.
那种感觉实际上是
And that feeling is actually being...
对各种大屠杀中
is for people who are symbols of victims
受害者的感同身受
of all kinds of horrendous genocides.
后来 库布里克的妻子谈到了
And of course, his wife has subsequently talked about,
他曾多么接近屠杀犹太人的电影
you know, how close he came to making his Holocaust movie,
*库布里克未拍摄的电影
剧本由其改编自
路易·伯格利的小说《战争谎言》
比如《雅利安证件》*但他越来越沮丧
The Aryan Papers, but that he got more and more
最终有了借口
and more depressed and was relieved
放弃拍摄
when he had an excuse not to do it.
他提到了《辛德勒的名单》 并说
He used Schindler's List as saying,
"啊 它已经完成了"
"Ah, it's already been done."
这给我敲了一个警钟
I mean, that struck a bell with me.
至今 我作为一名记者我 已经采访了
And I've done a lot of stories as a journalist
很多在研究
about people who study...
研究大屠杀或其中的受害者
either talked to people who are victims of horrors or study it.
弗洛伊德将此称为情感感染
And there's... Freud talked about it as the contagion.
沮丧渗入你的体内
The depression seeps into you.
你知道 库布里克关于一个问题
It's... you know what... Kubrick had a wonderful comment
有一个著名的言论
about this when somebody asked him.
"你的电影向我们展示了
"Isn't it true that your movies are showing us
人性的可怕 对不对？
just the horrendous side of humanity.
非常的消极"
You know, that's awful bleak."
库布里克答到
And Kubrick said,
"但是我的电影里也有一些非常积极的东西
”"Ah, but there's something very positive about it as well.
那就是 不管怎么样
And that is, it shows at the very least
我的电影让我们认识到了恐惧是什么"
that we can get our minds around what that horror is."
在电影的一开始 丹尼
And Danny, from the beginning,
就充满着各种疑问
has his mind all over the problem.
他在看 在思考
He's looking at it.
丹尼反复的骑车 骑上骑下
In a way, Danny's big wheeling back and forth,
从某种程度上来说
up and down the hallways...
他是在认识这个酒店
Danny is learning that hotel.
他也在认识恐惧
He's learning all the horrors.
他看到了恐惧
He's seeing them.
但它们只属于过去
But they're just in the past,
哈洛伦告诉了他那个秘密
and Hallorann gave him the secret.
他说 "记住 丹尼"
He said, "Remember, Danny."
记住托尼说的话
Remember what Tony tells him.
记住哈洛伦说的
Remember what Mr. Hallorann said:
"他们就像书里的照片
"They're just like pictures in a book.
他们不是真的"
They're not real."
这是一门很重要的课程
Now, that's a really important lesson.
那些过来人 看到历史的人
People who shine, who see through history,
他们知道 过去都是不存在的
understand that the past simply does not exist
除了一个地方
except in one place.
那就是对于现在的即使记忆
And that's the present tense instant of the mind, remembering.
这就是一个你可以到达但是
That is, exactly... that is a place you can go to somehow
却不存在的地方
and yet it doesn't exist.
因此哈洛伦对丹尼说
And so Hallorann tells Danny,
"你会看到一些恐怖的东西"
"You're gonna see some horrible things."
很明显 他告诉他
Apparently, he told him.
"你会看到一些恐怖的东西
"You're gonna see some horrible things,
但是记住 他们不是真的
but remember, they're not real.
他们就像书里的照片
They're like pictures in a book.
他们不再存在"
They no longer exist."
这就是不感到恐惧的关键
That's a key to not getting depressed about it.
这也是...
And that's...
你知道 这是一部关于过去的电影...
You see, this is a movie about what the past...
关于过去所带来的冲击
how the past impinges, any past,
以及如何克服他们
and about how to get over that
如何避免成为一名历史的受害者
and how not to be a victim of history.
而如果你对我的观点有所怀疑
You know, if you doubt what I've written about it,
那么去看电影吧
just go see the movie.
我已经通过观赏它解决了这一切疑惑
I've figured all this out from just seeing the movie.
它在那儿
It's there.
很明显 而且许多人看了电影之后都会说
It's obvious, and most people who went and saw the movie said,
"天哪 它就在那儿"
"Oh, my goodness. It is there."
如何看《闪灵》
- 走你
- Okay.
我对《闪灵》可以说是着了迷
Yeah, I was, I mean, obsessed with The Shining
我看了所有网上对它的分析
and reading all the online analyses of it
我也是一个
and was particularly a big fan
分析《闪灵》影评人的脑残粉
of the MSTRMND's lengthy analysis of it.
影评人拒绝我们的采访
他有一句话一直在我脑海里
And he had one phrase that kind of stuck in my mind,
那就是  《闪灵》是一部
that The Shining was a film
值得反复观看的电影
meant to be seen forwards and backwards.
他并不是说要一直看
And, I mean, he didn't mean at the same time.
他是说 在那个镜子的暗喻下
He meant that in, with the mirror form metaphor
镜子是这部电影的核心
that's central to the film
电影中...
that things, you know...
贯穿这整部电影的
that things forwards and backwards
前前后后的情节
happen throughout the film.
比如 电影中人们向后倒退
That... people walk backwards in the film, you know,
人们把话倒过来说
people talk backwards.
- 杀谋杀
- Redrum. Redrum.
《闪灵》开头
《2001：太空漫游》
- 如果你倒序放这部电影
- You know, if you reverse the film,
格式上它很像《2001：太空漫游》
it has a format similar to 2001.
一些相同的事情发生了
All these kind of things happen.
《闪灵》的最后
《2001：太空漫游》的开头
在《闪灵》的最后
At the end of The Shining,
他变成了一个咆哮的猿人
he's reduced to a screaming ape,
就像《2001：太空漫游》的开头部分里
just like in the beginning of 2001,
那些咆哮的猩猩
there are screaming apes.
在奇景影院和朋友说了这些
But I was talking to my pals at the Spectacle Theater,
和他们一起重看了很多次
riffing about experimental ways of showing films.
他们说 你不觉得你？
And they were like, "Well, do you think
可以做点儿什么吗？
you could come up with something,
在这儿放给大家看看
you know, to show here?"
我说 "对 我们应该做的就是
I was like, "Sure, what we should do is we should show
把《闪灵》的开头和结尾同时放
The Shining forwards and backwards at the same time.
不需要很创造性
You know not... let's not be creative.
只是把电影倒着放
Let's just actually reverse the film
镜像的 重叠的播放它
and show it exactly mirrored, superimposed."
第一个画面是清澈的湖
The first image is of the reflective lake.
最后一个画面是照片上的
And the last image is of the inscription
题词
on the photograph,
照片上 杰克被定格
in which Jack is frozen for all time...
上面写着1921年7月4号派对 远望酒店
The "Overlook Hotel, July 4th Ball, 1921."
这些重叠让照片看起来...
So those superimposed make it...
看起来像一张明信片 一封邀请函
kind of make it seem like a postcard, like an invitation.
就像...
Like...
"欢迎参加7月4号湖边的派对
""Come to the July 4th Ball here in Crater Lake."
这里还有一个很酷炫的地方
There's a really cool part where, like, you know,
直升机跟随着杰克的轿车
the helicopters are following his car
演职表中 他的名字向上滚动
and his name scrolls up in the credits
接着 和汽车碰在一起
and, like, meets the car, right...
并且处在照片格的位置
right in the same position where the grid of photographs,
而那张照片又刚好是他自己
right in that photograph that he's trapped in.
所以 他的轿车 他的名字和他的照片
So his car, his name and his photograph
在那一秒排成了一条线
all line up for one second.
酷炫
Pretty cool.
呵呵呵呵呵
面试场景...拍得很厉害
The interview has a, like... it's great.
当他们枯燥地
While they're talking about...
谈论着酒店以前的谋杀时
you know, very dryly about all the murders that happened,
在叠化中看
like, you know, in the superimposition,
杰克拿着斧头 发了疯一样
Jack's running around with an axe going bananas, you know.
同样精彩的叠化还有很多
There's a lot of just great, great, great superimpositions
比如人们的脸部重合
of people's faces lining up, like Jack's...
杰克在濒死时的表情
Jack's, like, got the death look,
在丹尼吃三明治的时候
and he's staring through Danny's face
盯着他
as Danny's eating a sandwich.
还有很多...很多...
Then there's a lot of things... there's a lot of, like...
还有一些搞笑
there's a... you know, there's some fun jokes,
但又严肃的地方
but then there's serious stuff where,
比如...
like, you...
丹尼出现的幻觉...
where the hallucination... the visions that Danny has,
看起来就像覆盖
where you'll see them,
在其他场景的上面
like, overlaid on top of other situations.
例如 那对双胞胎女孩覆盖在温迪上面
Like the twin girls are overlaid on top of Wendy,
如果你仔细观察
which, if you study the film,
你会发现那对双胞胎和温迪有所关联
you see that the twins are associated with Wendy.
她们就像温迪的视觉对应点
They're like her, like, visionary counterpart.
电影中的象征符号...
All the symbols in the movie start...
在反复的叠化展现出来中
overlap in the superimposition, backwards/forwards superimposition.
被谋杀的双胞胎叠化在杰克的脸上
The murdered twins are overlaid across Jack's face,
让他看起来像个小丑
and he looks like a clown.
让他有了一个小丑面罩
It makes like a clown mask,
而四处遍布的鲜血
and there's blood everywhere
就像在他的嘴唇上
and, like, blood on his lips.
血液从他的眼睛里流出来
And blood coming out of his eyes.
就像丹尼...
And, like, you know, Danny takes it...
丹尼用双手盖住脸
you know, like, Danny has his hands over his face,
而杰克从他的头部往外看
and it's... Jack is looking out from his head,
然后丹尼张开手向外窥视 看到了格雷迪
and then he open... he, like, peeks out and he sees Grady.
接着是格雷迪和杰克在下一个
And then Grady and Jack continue their conversation
场景的对话
into the next scene,
就是丹尼看电视的那个场景
which is where he's watching television.
看起来他们的嘴唇...
And it's like they have this...
就像在电视里一样
their lips are, like, in the TV.
杰克和格雷迪的嘴唇在电视上
Jack and Grady's lips are in the TV.
而窗户变成了他们的面罩
And these masks are formed by the windows.
看上去像丹尼在想象出这一切
And ifs like Danny's envisioning this.
丹尼在想象...
Danny's envisioning...
看到了格雷迪和杰克之间的约定
you know, envisioning the pact between Grady and Jack.
就像他潜入卧室
Like, he goes into... he sneaks into the bedroom,
穿过杰克脑袋的右边
like, right through Jack's head,
刚好在他们中间
right in between them.
就像那个场景...
And just like that scene is...
丹尼在试探他的爸爸
that's the scene where Danny is testing
问他"你喜不喜...
his father, like, "Do you really, you know!"...
你喜不喜欢这个地方？
"Do you like this place?
你不会伤害我们的 对吧？"
You're not gonna hurt us, are you?"
就像丹尼已经知道爸爸迷失了自己
Like, Danny kind of knows that his dad has lost it.
终于翻完这个意淫狂了 T^T
最后一组镜头是关于1921年
The last shot is 1921,
第一个镜头是在路上
and the first shot is of the road.
*酒店竣工是在1909年 不知道这里的1921代表什么
厄尔曼提到它是在1921年*结束
Ullman mentions that it was finished in 1921.
所以这是首尾呼应
So it's, again, it's a way of returning the narrative
回到最初
back to the beginning.
卧槽又来一段意淫。。
远望酒店
1921年7月4日派对
237 房间
- 哈洛伦先生 237房间里有什么？
- Mr. Hallorann, what is in room 237?
- 啥都没
- Nothing.
237号房间里什么都没
There ain't nothing in room 237.
总之你不要进去
But you ain't got no business going in there anyway,
离它远点
so stay out.
- 在237那个情趣房里
- In the sex room, 237,
我们看到了这个美丽的妖妇
where we see this beautiful, sexual temptress,
之后变成了腐烂的尸体
who then becomes a rotting body...
十分现实而形象的腐尸
realistically depicted as a rotting body...
而对地毯的设计 总体上利用一些
the design on the rug shows basically the most...
几何形的圆弧曲线体现了
in geometric form with round curves...
性行为
the act of intercourse itself,
一个接着一个接着一个接着一个
one after another after another after another,
像一幅
sort of like a picture
传宗接代 生产生命的画
of down through the generations of what produces life.
当你回到走廊 进入了一个更大的社会
You go back out in the hallway, in the larger society,
那些圆弧曲线的地毯的设计
and the round curves of that very same design
变成了六边形
have become hexagons,
不再是那么圆滑 而变得更像是
not so nice and round, and a little bit more
六边形的蜂窝
like the beehive hexagon
像是历史的走廊
but down the whole corridors of history.
我觉得库布里克在这里使用的影像
I think he's got an image of it there,
是要表达家庭中的男性
so he's talking about the family of man,
既包括基本家庭
both in an individual nuclear family
也包括了人类的发展历史
and in the whole course of our genetic history.
- 当丹尼进入了237房间
- Once Denny enters room 237, like, that's...
就有点像激活了
that kind of is, like, the activation
电影的余下部分
of the rest of the movie.
那就是让杰克最终发疯的原因
Like, that's what causes Jack to go insane finally.
那就是把哈洛伦带回酒店的原因
That's what brings Hallorann to the hotel.
237房间就像...
Like, the room 237 is, like, is sort of this...
我将它与《2001：太空漫游》里的神秘屋
I mean, I compare it to the mysterious hotel room
进行比较
at the end of 2001,
这个奇怪的...
where there's...
奇怪的房间
It's this strange, strange place
某种程度上 转变了故事后续的发展
that somehow, like, transforms the rest of the narrative.
《闪灵》是在一座山上拍摄（发生）的
The Shining takes place on the top of a mountain
这是一个...
in kind of like a, you know,
魔幻的 变形的环境
magical shape-shifting environment.
走出...
And, like, travel is...
走出它就是...
traveling out of it is...
它不像《2001：太空漫游》 感觉自己是在哪儿游玩
You know, instead of 2001, where you're traveling to something,
《闪灵》的重点是走出 是逃脱
the point of The Shining is to escape, is to travel out.
而237房间
And room 237 is, like...
它就像这个酒店的逃生舱
it's kind of like the escape pod of... of the hotel.
如果你把2 3 7 相乘 你得到42
- If you multiply the numbers 2, 3 and 7, you get 42.
我承认我也许在垂死挣扎
Now, I admit, perhaps I'm grasping at straws there,
但它是电影中的一个始终如一的参考
but it is consistent with the pattern of reference in the film.
- 另一件事在我的电影《库布里克的奥德赛》中
- Another thing which my film Kubrick's Odyssey
会揭露
really reveals
在那个丹尼玩小车的场景中
is the carpeting on the floor
他穿着阿波罗十一号的毛衣
during the famous Danny scene,
站在地毯上
where he stands up with his Apollo 11 shirt.
地毯的图案与39-A*发射台完全对应
The patterns in the carpeting exactly match launch pad 39-A.
*位于佛罗里达州肯尼迪航天中心
包括车道和一切一切
You know, even the driveway and everything.
不知道你有没有注意到 当丹尼站起来时 地毯上的图案
And if you notice in that shot, the pattern on the rug changes
变化过了
when Danny stands up.
棕色条纹指向丹尼
棕色条纹在丹尼身后
地毯的方向被调过了
- The carpet's reversed,
那个棕线不见了
and there's no pathway there anymore.
那个球顺着滚向丹尼的线条
The pathway that the ball took rolling down towards Danny
不见了
is gone now.
因为地毯被倒过来铺
It's no longer there 'cause it's reversed.
你感觉到了终止
And you get a sense of a closure.
六边形关上了
Now the hexagon is closed.
就像他被关在了里面
It's almost like he's been closed in.
《闪灵》之后
- 《闪灵》上映七年后
- Seven years after The Shining had come out,
让我吃惊的是 没有人可以
to my surprise, nobody had written,
写下我所说的那些
as far as I could tell,
除了电影中的那个家庭和酒店
about what the major themes of the movie were,
所带给我们的让人欣喜的恐惧之外
beyond the delightfully scary immediate story
电影的真正主题是什么
of the family and the hotel itself.
而我的确在欧洲某个地方写着一部小说
And I was actually doing a story somewhere over in Europe,
有人在电话里跟我说 《全金属外壳》的
and I was told over the phone that the posters were out
海报张贴出来了
for Full Metal Jacket.
我问了海报上的描述
I asked about the description,
他说 是一个和平标志和一句话
and I was told it had a peace sign right next to the words
"天生杀人狂"
"Born to kill."
然后我说 "哦天哪
And I said, "Oh, my goodness.
他的下一部应该还是同样的主题"
His next movie's gonna be about some of the same themes."
总之 艾玛我去
Anyway, I thought, "My goodness."
我推测它的主题会很明显
I had presumed that it would have become obvious,
所以我想...什么情况？
so I thought, "What the heck?
我要看看能不能写一篇文章来让
"I'll just see if I can write an article about it
人们看《全金属外壳》的时候更觉得有趣
to give people more fun when they see Full Metal Jacket,
更广义的让大家知道 他的上一部电影
to know what his last movie was about,
在说些什么
in larger senses.
只工作不玩耍,聪明的孩子也变傻
- 我遭受到了许多在美国宇航局工作人员的谴责
- I've gotten a lot of flak from people who work for NASA.
而我想告诉他们
And, you know, I want to tell them, that I, you know,
我不是说我们没上过月球
I'm not saying that we didn't go to the moon.
我也不是说他们所创造出
And I'm not saying that their technology
的科技
that they helped build
不伟大 不好 等等
isn't great and awesome and everything.
我只是说 我们所看到的 是假的
I'm just saying that what we saw was faked.
而且我已经用前屏投影
And I know I have it proved
证明了这一点
with the front-screen projection process.
目前为止 政府所做的
As far as what the government has done,
老实说 我十分期待明年我的税收
I fully expect my taxes to be audited next year,
被审计
to be honest with you.
我也被正式访问过
And, you know, I've had visitations, you know.
而且他们肯定在监视着我
And they're definitely watching me for sure,
而且他们并不乐意我正接受采访
and they're not too happy with what's going on here.
我认为他们很担心
And I think they're probably very worried
下一部电影
about the next film.
而且它肯定会是一部爆炸性的电影
And that one will be the really explosive film.
- 假期里 我们走在哥斯达黎加
- We were walking along the beach on vacation
的沙滩边
with some people in Costa Rica.
这是个美好的经历
I had this delightful experience.
我们和一对来自旧金山的小情侣
We were walking along with a young couple
一起散步
who were from San Francisco.
我们走了很久
And it was a long walk.
我们穿过了一个美丽的丛林
的We'd gone through this big, beautiful jungle.
然后我们从沙滩边走回来
And were coming back on the beach
走到我们扎营的地方
to walk back to where the tent camp was.
然后我们开始...
And the guy started...
我们开始谈论库布里克
we started chatting about Kubrick.
我说 "库布里克很伟大"
I said, "Oh, Kubrick's great,"
那个人说：
And the guy said, "You know,
"《闪灵》 实际上是关于美国印第安人的电影"
The Shining, it's actually about the American Indians."
我说 "真的吗？"
I said, "Really?"
然后他接着说下去 而我一直说 "真的吗？"
And he went on talking, and I said, "Really?"
在他跟我说这些的时候
And I just couldn't resist just playing dumb for while
我就是忍不住装傻充愣
while he told me the whole thing.
我也很开心
I was delighted!
那一天 愤怒之日
Dies irae, dies illa
库布里克建立了一个同步的场景
- Kubrick just sets up synchronous space.
他的电影...
His movies are...
他们在彼此之间创造出了共时性场景
they create synchronous situations in themselves.
这个人 他嘴上说
There's this man who says, you know,
"真是好玩的派对 不是吗？"
"Quite a party, isn't it?"
库布里克为什么要设立一个
Why did Kubrick put him there,
头裂开的人在这里？
with the split down his head?
为什么不放在其他场景？
Why did he put him there?
我苦思冥想
And I was contemplating that.
然后我儿子进来了
And in comes my son.
他那时九岁
And he was nine years old at the time.
不知道我正在忙些什么
And he didn't know what I was working on.
他走进来 跟我说了一个故事
And he came in, and he began to tell me a story.
他说 "这个是我刚想到的"
And he said, "I've just thought this up."
故事里 人物的头被闪电劈开了
And his characters head was split open with a chaos bolt.
然后人物说 "我的头裂开了"
And the character says, "Talk about a splitting headache."
而从他的头里跳出了
And out of the contents of his head
一个小人 这才是真正的他
leaps a small person who is his real self.
然后他跑了 用一个尖锐的声音喊着
And it goes running off, saying in a high, squeaky voice,
"别想了 我回家了“”
"Forget this. I'm going home."
这就是一个极好的共时性
And, yeah, I thought that was really stunning synchronicity,
我是说 你已经看到了所有的元素
I mean, 'cause you've got all the elements there.
你有了斧头
You've got the ax.
你被雷电击中
You've got the whole idea of the lightning bolt,
闪电劈在那个人的头上
the chaos bolt, striking the person's head,
劈裂的头
the splitting headache.
还有托尼
You've got Tony...
托尼尖锐的声音
Tony's squeaky voice, yeah.
我认为这是一个很好的共时性场景
I thought that was quite a synchronicity.
- 对于库布里克 人们总对他
- One can always argue that Kubrick
是否有意为之争论不休
had only some or even none of these in mind.
但是我们从后现代主义电影批评中了解到
But we all know from postmodern film criticism
作者目的 只是各种艺术作品中的一部分
that author intent is only part of the story of any work of art.
这就意味着 不用去管创作者
And those meanings are there regardless
对作品是否有主观意识
of whether the creator of the work was conscious of them.
- 我认为...
- I think... if you want to know what I think,
我认为 酒店是如此的诡异
I think the hotel is so whacked out
以至于我在开始时 根本不知道
that I don't have any clue what's going on
发生了什么
from the beginning.
当你坐下好好思考时
When you really sit and think about it, I mean...
我是说 因为整部电影如此诡异
because the whole thing is so whacked out,
如此的分散
and it's so not put together...
它是如此...每件事都显得不合适
it's so... everything is so wildly out of place
以至于当你...思考 调查的更多
that when you... the more... the closer you get
你也就会看到得更多
into looking at things, the more you look at them.
这就像 在《大开眼界》里的场景
It's kind of like, you know, the scene in Eyes Wide Shut
当比尔出去 又回来
where Bill goes... you know, he returns.
他找寻自己的脚印
He retraces his footsteps,
他回到了那个大楼里
and he goes back to the mansion where he was.
但是他被告知 停止打探
And he's told, you know, to stop your inquiries.
他们不会告诉你任何内幕的
They will serve you no purpose.
这与《闪灵》很相像
It's almost like it gets to that with The Shining.
你越是看的清楚 越是注意他们
The more you magnify things, the more you look at them,
你得到的也越少 因为它是如此的混乱
the less purpose it serves 'cause it's so out of whack.
在开头时 这一切都没有用
None of it makes sense from the beginning.
这里一定有许多
- There must be a lot of stuff in there
人们没有注意到的东西
that nobody has yet seen,
所以人们应该一直观看它
so people ought to keep watching it.
- 但是 为什么库布里克让电影这么复杂呢
- But why would he make the movie so complicated?
*爱尔兰意识流小说家
- 我是说 为什么乔伊斯*要写《芬尼根彻夜祭》？
- Yeah, I mean, but why did Joyce write Finnegan's Wake?
这就像一扇开着的门
It's a way of, like, opening doors
就像从密封的现实
from, like, a hermetically sealed reality
进入了可能性
into possibilities.
这也是困住人们 比如我 的一种方式
And it's also a way of trapping someone like me.
困住那个想要寻找线索 并坚持下去的人
Like, who goes looking for clues and, like, keeps finding them.
还有一件事情就是 我要永远被困在
And next thing you know, you're like, Man, I've been...
这个酒店里了
I've been trapped in this hotel forever.
这是我梦寐以求的地方
I'm dreaming about this place.
我就像杰克
You know, I'm like Jack.
我就是 只工作不玩耍,聪明的孩子也变傻
I'm, like, all work and no play.
或者说我只玩耍不工作
Or the other way around.
这并不重要...
It doesn't really matter, like...
你就像在一个圆圈里
You're, like, in this loop.
但是你有逃出去的线路
But, you know, there are escape routes, like the...
我觉得库布里克把线路藏在了
like, I think he puts escape routes
那个迷宫里 地图里
into it, into this maze, into this trap.
我是说 有很多出去的路
I mean, there are ways out of it.
丹尼通过不断的
And Danny finds a way out of it,
找寻自己的脚印
you know, by retracing his steps,
发现了其中一条
by going backwards and forwards.
而你一旦开始学习
And once you start, you know, studying, you know,
共时性和象征性
synchronicity and symbolism,
突然间
then, like, suddenly, like,
你注意到了自己的生活
you're noticing in your own life,
事物开始跳出来
like, things start popping out.
那些你之前没有注意到的事物
Things that you hadn't noticed before, you know, like your...
那些被长期学习所改变的观点
point of view is being altered by your study.
这就像...
And, you know, it's the...
量子物理学
It's quantum physics, you know, like,
你的观察力 情绪
the act of observing, like, affects
那些被观察到的事物
you know, the thing observed.
- 嗨 劳埃德
- Hi, Lloyd.
- 是的
- Yeah.
我的意思是 这变的诡异
Yeah, I mean, it gets weird because, like, I'd... you know,
我一直被这件事困扰 我一直在家里休养
as I've been obsessing over this thing, you know, I've been home,
我失业已经有一阵子了
like, I'd been out of work for a while, like...
我还有个儿子
I have a small son.
我们打算搬到一个
You know, we're thinking of moving out to, like,
与世隔绝的地方
somewhere isolated.
我是说 事情变的奇怪起来
I mean, things get strange, you know?
就好像...
Like, you're...
就好像我的生活
like, wow, my life has actually become
成了《闪灵》
The Shining, you know?
翻译 SlimChen
制作 SlimChen
校对 SlimChen
=感谢观看=